<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vnmasking of the politique atheist By I.H. Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
            <author>Hull, John, 1569 or 70-1627.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13934</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114293</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849519</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849519</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14671</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03817)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14671)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1632:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vnmasking of the politique atheist By I.H. Batcheler of Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>Hull, John, 1569 or 70-1627.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Read] for Ralph Howell, dwelling in Paules Church-yard neere the great North doore, at the signe of the White Horse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>I.H. = John Hull.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; tightly bound and pages trimmed affecting text; signature F2 verso-end from the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge) copy spliced at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE VNMASKING OF THE POL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LITIQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E ATHEIST.</p>
            <p>By I. H. Batcheler of <hi>Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AT LONDON Printed for <hi>Ralph Howell,</hi> dwelling in <hi>Paules Church-yard neere the great</hi> North doore, at the Signe of the White Horſe. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O render thee a reaſon (Chriſtian reader) of publiſhing this ſhorte Treatiſe: It is in a worde the contrary to <hi>Iſocrates</hi> anſwer vnto a queſtion out of time, ſaying; <hi>Quae ego noui, temporis huius non ſunt, quae verò exigit tempus hoc, ego neſcio:</hi> Thoſe things which J know, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long not vnto this time, and thoſe which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine vnto this time, I know not. But we ſay, the things which belong vnto this time, wofull experience hath made vs for to know, and the things which we know, the miſery of this time commaunds vs to report. For are not theſe the dayes whereof our Sauiour Chriſt, and his Apoſtles ſo long agoe forepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied, wherein charity ſhould wax colde,<note place="margin">Math. 24. 2. Theſ. 2. 2. Tim. 3.</note> and faith ſhould ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>appeare, wherein men ſhould be ſlide backs from Chriſt, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates from his true religion, wherein they ſhould be louers of themſelues, couetous, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpeakers, diſobedient, vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>keful, vnholy, true-breakers, falſe accuſers, deſpiſers of them that are good, traitors, headdy, high-minded,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:3"/>louers of pleaſure more then louers of good, hauing a ſhew of godlineſſe, but haue denied the power thereof: yea wherein men are become, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſers, Newters, Temporiſers, Athiſts. And the principall cauſe hereof muſt needs be the corrupt nature of man bending too too much vnto Papiſtry. For compare theſe times with the dayes of yore, when Papiſtry ſwayed the ſcepter, and you ſhall ſee the effects of both times to be alike. About the yeare 363. at what time the world began to decline; <hi>Anthony</hi> ſaw in a dreame, as it were Hogges, which trode vnder the feet their altars: &amp; waking ſaid, that the Church ſhalbe once againe ſpoiled and diſperſed by whoremongers, adulterers, and monſtrous men, which propheſie <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> noteth to be againſt the leacherous and voluptuous life of Prieſts and Monkes. This propheſie began to take effect about the yeare 604. when papiſtry did preuaile, the Popedome flouriſh, and true doctrine loſt her puritie. For about the yeare 688. <hi>Theodore</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Rauenna</hi> was greatly hated of the Cleargie, becauſe he ſough to keep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them in good manners. But to come vnto the time wherein Papiſtry did rage and ſhew her
<pb facs="tcp:14671:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>full forces,<note place="margin">Anno. 1126. Anno. 1140. Hugo C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. poſtil. in S. lohan.</note> which was about 100. yeares after Chriſt, and then ſhall you finde <hi>Hugo</hi> of <hi>Saxon</hi> mightely complaining againſt diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. <hi>Barnard</hi> calling the Prelates, Pilates, and the Church men miniſters of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: yea that all the vniuerſitie of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did conſpire againſt Chriſt.<note place="margin">Anno. 1157.</note> Now was <hi>Iohn of Saresburie</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chartres</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to write a booke intituled <hi>Obiur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorium,</hi> pertaining to chiding, rebuking, and finding fault, ſo greatly was he mooued with the wickedneſſe of thoſe times: wherein the Popes did ſucceede rather <hi>Romulus</hi> in murthers and Parricides,<note place="margin">Speculum.</note> then <hi>S. Peter</hi> in feeding the flock: as Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> the fourth oftentimes confeſſed. Now began <hi>Peter de Blois</hi> to call the Popes officials helliſh Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies, and the cleargie <hi>Syria, Edom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1240.</note> Calues of <hi>Bethel,</hi> Idols of <hi>Egypt,</hi> the fat of <hi>Samaria,</hi> Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and earneſtly exhorteth to depart out of <hi>Babylon.</hi> Then complained <hi>Peter de Vinea</hi> of the inſaciable couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Pope, and the filthineſſe of the Clergie. <hi>Guillame le Orfeince</hi> prooued the Pope to be Antichriſt, <hi>Rome Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1260.</note> and the Prelates the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers of Antichriſt. Now was there a booke found <hi>De pericu'is</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:4"/>made of the dangers of the world. Now ſtood vp <hi>Peter Caſiodorus</hi> vexing his ſoule for the wickedneſſe of thoſe times. So did <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thias Pariſienſis, Iohn Wicleffe, Iohn Hus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1306. Anno. 1370.1405, &amp;c. Bridenba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius.</note> and many others, to beholde the uniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thoſe dayes, wherein <hi>receſſit lex à ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus, à principibus iuſtitia, conſili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um à ſenioribus, à populo fides, &amp;c.</hi> The Lawe departed from the Prieſt, Juſtice from the Prince, counſell from the Senator, faith from the people<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loue from parents, reuerence from ſubiects, charity from Prelates, religion from Monkes, honeſty from young men, pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie from teachers ſtudy from ſcholers, equity from Iudges, concord from Cittizens, feare from ſeruants, and fellowſhip from the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, truth from the Marchant, vertue from the Noble, chaſtitie from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin, humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie from the widdow, loyalty from the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, and patience from the poore. Were theſe then and ſuch like the effects of Papiſtry in former ages, and ſhall we behold them againe to enter vpon the world, and not labour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue the cauſe? God forbid. The conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration therefore of theſe lamentable times hath wroong from me this briefe Treatiſe. Wherein thou maieſt behold the very map
<pb facs="tcp:14671:4"/>of Papiſtrie: a doctrine turning the truth of God into a lye, and religion into ſuperſtition: perſwading men to all vngodlineſſe, and yet ouerſhadowing all with the ſhew of religion: Arming the ſubiect againſt the Prince,<note place="margin">See the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in Ireland.</note> and yet defend it by the beaſtly Bull of Popiſh excommunication. Sowing ſedition and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the land, yet dare appeare vnto the Lords of the councell as men blameleſſe and religious, as did that Machieuillian Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh practiſer (as the Prieſts of his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion doe terme him) <hi>Parſons</hi> that Iugling Ieſuite: whereas they meane nothing els, but the vtter ſubuerſion of religion and the ſtate, as plainly appeareth by the workes of Sir <hi>Francis Haſtings</hi> and <hi>D. Sutliue.</hi> Thus are they well practiſed in Machieuel,<note place="margin">Lip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>us de duplici con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dia.</note> turning religion into pollicie: Imitating ſeditious <hi>Clodius, Qui cum eſſet religionis non hoſtis ſolum, ſed etiam contemptor, tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſceleribus, quae in tribunatu patrauit, reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem et auſpicia fuit auſus praetexere:</hi> who, albeit he were not only an enimy to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but alſo a deſpiſer and contemner of the ſame, yet he pretended religion in behalfe of all the villainies he committed in his Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buneſhip. Way then the end of this ſhorte
<pb facs="tcp:14671:5"/>Treatiſe, and let vs be more thankefull vnto God for the riches of his reuealed truth. Firſt it vnmaskes the Politicians, that ſute religion after the faſhion of their pollicie. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly it forewarnes and ſo forearmes thee againſt theſe popiſh charmes that now flye about the land, leaſt vnwittingly thou be inchanted with them. Thirdly it giues thee a taſte what benefits thou ſhalt receiue by entertaining Papiſtry, namely hereſie, polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſuperſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, Atheiſme, and all vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe. Fourthly it deſciphers vnto thee the enuious, murdering, and cruell nature of a right Papiſt, that hangs his whole religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Popes ſleeue,<note place="margin">Lipſiusvbi prius.</note> namely to be ſuch, <hi>qui ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iiciunt culos ſaepe ad hanc patriam, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> è faucibus ereptam dolent, qui vexil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum purpuratae Romanae belluae (O Deus immortalis auerte quaeſo hoc omen) in media defixuros ſe minitantur, qui non praedam ſed vitam, non ſeruitutem, ſed ſanguinem concupiſcunt: quibus nullus ludus iucundior eſt, quàm cruor, quàm caedes, quàm ante oculos trucidatio inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centium.</hi> Which often cast their eyes vpon this our countrie, which they greatly ſorrow is by Gods aide deliuered from their ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:5"/>in the midſt whereof (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) they threaten one day to diſplay the banner, and ſet vp the Enſigne of the purple Romiſh beaſt, who deſire not our good, but our bloud, neither thirſt after our liuings only, but alſo our liues: in whoſe eyes there is no play ſo pleaſant, as to beholde maſſacres, heare of murders, &amp; ſee the ſlaughters of ſilly innocents. Laſtly, it armes thee with truth by vnfoulding of the contrary, which truth God graunt vs to embrace to his glory, our health, and the countries good, which God no doubt begins to viſit for the ſinnes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, but eſpecially for the ſinne of Apoſtaſie, backſliding, and forſaking the ture religion,<note place="margin">Note the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clipſe of the moone, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. 29. 1601. and of the ſunne Decemb. 14. Yea two other Eclipſes of the moone are to happen this yeare. Thunder and lightning very common this Chriſtmas. Socrat. hiſt. 3.</note>to vphold the kingdome of Satan, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the doctrine of Antichriſt: which grieuous ſinne (eſpecially after ſo long ſunne ſhine of the Goſpell) the Sunne bluſheth to looke vpon, and the Moone is aſhamed to behold. The heauens roare and thunder to conſider, and the ayre ſindeth forth his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and threatneth with his lightning to wound from heauen all ſuch as with the Apoſtate <hi>Iulian</hi> reuolt from their profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and vndermine the faith of Christ.
<pb facs="tcp:14671:6"/>Yea the Earth,<note place="margin">An earthquake 1601. Decemb. 24.</note> the ſtable earth begins now to quauer, and to ſhake, as being ouerburd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with our ſinnes, and too weake to beare the waight of our iniquities, eſpecially to ſupport this ſinne,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. Tripart. lib. 4. cap. 10.</note> this heauie ſinne of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacie and irreligion, giuing vs warning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it open, as ſometime it did <hi>Antioche</hi> ready to receiue the hereſie of <hi>Arius,</hi> that if we leaue not off betimes to welcome Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, and to entertaine his armio of hereſie and Atheiſme, it will one day ſwallow vs vp quicke for conſpiring with the enemies of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Num. 16.</note> as ſometimes it did <hi>Corath, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,</hi> and <hi>Abiram.</hi> God graunt that other mens harmes may teach vs to beware.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. H.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:6"/>
            <head>The vnmasking of the <hi>politique Atheist.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Lindfolded</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiliſme coulde eſpie Atheiſme in <hi>Diagoras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero de nat. deor. lib. 1. Damaſ. lib. 1. orthodox fid. cap. 3.</note> and <hi>Theodorus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there was a God, the knowledge of whome is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ingrafted and bred in vs by nature.<note place="margin">Reſcius Wright &amp;c.</note> But quick-ſighted Papiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, can diſcrie Atheiſme in the true Chriſtian, becauſe he defies the Popes whome Chriſt and his Apoſtles haue taught vs to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt. O that the Papiſt could as well diſcerne his Lady Enuy, that
<pb facs="tcp:14671:7"/>quickens his ſight, and his Lorde Sathan that lends him light, then would he blame the Iewes ſight, and his owne eyes,<note place="margin">7. Iohn. 20.</note> the one for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deuill in Chriſt the head, and the other for beholding diueliſh Atheiſme in the Chriſtian his member. Yea then would they ſee that Satan is the maſter builder of their Church,<note place="margin">Tuſcul. quaeſt. 1. Cicero et de Nat. deor. lib. 1. 1. Rom. Act. 14 Acts. 17. Ioh. 5. Epheſ. 2.</note> and Atheiſme the chiefe foundation of their king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. For what is Papiſme? a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying there is a God? No, ſeeing no Barbarian (excepting ſome fewe) was ſo barbarous, howbeit, not exempted from Atheiſme. What then doth Papiſme acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge a Godhead, but deny the perſons? Not ſo neither, for they confeſſe <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, and crye <hi>templum domini, templum domini,</hi> we, and none but we are the Church. How then can they
<pb facs="tcp:14671:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>confeſſe God, and yet deny God? Yea, why not, as well as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt,<note place="margin">2. Theſſal. 2. Aug. Ciu. 23, &amp; 19.</note> that ſits in the Temple and Church of God, and yet the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt enemy of his Chriſt? For the profeſſion of the Church ſerues him but for a vaile to couer his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſme, and for a viſard to colour his Atheiſme: ſeeing he both de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and defies Chriſt, his Goſpell, and the Godhead, by his doctrine, worſhip, and liuing, ſo erronious, ſuperſticious, and vngodly: for what is the kingdome of Popery, but hereſie, ſeeing heretiques are armies of Antichriſt? And what is the ſea of Rome,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. hom. 49. in Math.</note> but an huge Ocean of hereſies? wherein <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and all heretiques doe take their pleaſure and repaſt. Here is Monkiſh poperie in imitation of Simonian Idolatry, worſhiping the Images of <hi>Francis</hi> and <hi>Clara.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Here in <hi>domo Dei presbyteri et Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi vendentes ſunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Roiard hom. Ser. 2. poſt dom. Latare.</note> Both Prieſts and Praelates make the houſe of God an houſe of Marchandies. Heere are Cardinals buying the Popedome, and Popes ſelling Chriſt and Chriſtendome.<note place="margin">Gyrolan Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tena.</note> Yea, here are the paines of Purgatorie to be bought off for money, and the pleaſures of Paradiſe to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for coine. Howbeit the Pope challengeth place <hi>authoritate Dei,</hi> by Gods authority. Fie fowle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouthd <hi>Florinian</hi> to vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pe the kingdome of the ſonne,<note place="margin">Bulla <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i quinti in Eliz.</note> and yet to challenge it as from the Father. Here may yee ſee Midwiues bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing,<note place="margin">Aug. haereſ. 66.</note> and a woman executing the office of the Popedome, and are not they moſt fearefull foes to the Pepucians?<note place="margin">Rom. char. part 2. ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 18.</note> But will you know their warres againſt <hi>Nouatius?</hi> They debarre Miniſters from ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable marriages,<note place="margin">Bellar. de bapt. lib 1. cap. 7.</note> and compell
<pb facs="tcp:14671:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>them to periſh in diſhonourable luſt: which was one among the greeuances that the <hi>Germans</hi> exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to Cardinall <hi>Campeius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiphan haereſ. 79.</note> that their Biſhops and Officials did not onely ſuffer Prieſts for their mony to haue concubines,<note place="margin">Theod. fab. hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ. lib. 3.</note> but compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led chaſte Prieſts to pay their tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, that ſo it might be lawfull for them to liue as they liſt.<note place="margin">Rhem. Acts. 21. ſect. 1.</note> O ſay not ſo, this is a chaſte generation. For thoſe that were their wiues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore orders,<note place="margin">Aug. haereſ. 87.</note> ſhall be their wiues ſtil, but their husbands ſhall not haue acceſſe vnto them: a crue of faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Abellians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oecolamp. Fox pag. 861.</note> And call you this a chaſte generation that condemne men for marriage? witneſſe <hi>Petrus Sponglerus</hi> in the yeare 1525.<note place="margin">Rhen. Anor. 1. Cor. 7. ſect. 8.</note> that call marriage the worſt ſort of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continencie: that ſay Prieſthood is prophaned by it: that dare af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that thoſe that are in <hi>carne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. mar. diſcou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſect 1</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>deo placere non poſſunt:</hi> that married perſons cannot pleaſe God,<note place="margin">Siricius. Epiſt. ad Him: Tarac.</note> that forbid prieſts marriages, leaſt they ſhould defile the ſacrament: and becauſe it is written <hi>ſancti eſtote:</hi> be yee holy.<note place="margin">Aqui. add 3. part. q. 53. art. 3</note> As if that were no holy thing, that was inſtituted by an holy author,<note place="margin">Innocent. diſt. 81. cap. propoſ.</note> bleſſed by an holy God, ordained at an holy time, ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated in an holy place, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed vnto holy perſons, as were <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Euah</hi> before their fall.<note place="margin">2. Gen. 74. 13 Heb. 4.</note> which the holy ſcripture calleth honorable vnto all men: and the ſacred <hi>Paphnutius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zozem. lib. 1. c. 23. Enemies 10 mariage were Tatian, Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſts, Euſtachi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Montaniſts, Priſcilia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s, Iuſtin, Peneus, Euſebius, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus de caſtro, &amp;c. Ang. haereſ. 25.</note> with all the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen</hi> councell in the yeare 315. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and acknowledged <hi>concubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum cum propria vxore caſlitatem eſſe,</hi> Copulation with a mans owne wife to be chaſtitie. Why then O you <hi>Tatian</hi> Papiſts and Eucratites exclude you <hi>coniugio vtentem</hi> mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried perſons from your order? why embraſe you Cainiſme for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding
<pb facs="tcp:14671:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>him to bee conſecrated Biſhop,<note place="margin">Hierom ad Oceanurr.</note> that marrieth another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his firſt wife be dead? <hi>quam hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſin ſequitur Romana eccleſia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eraſmus.</note> Why then yee ſacred Fryars, and chaſte <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> do you contemne that honorable calling? as if a married woman do come within your cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, it muſt be waſhed and cleanſed after her with holy water.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 5. c. 18. Alex. pope. 3. ad Epiſ Exon. de ſpont. c. Com.</note> And why clap you hands rather with <hi>Montanus</hi> teaching the diſſolution of marriage: then with God, that forbids to ſeperate that, which he hath conioyned? yea and with the <hi>Nicolaitans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Apoc. 6.</note> had rather vſe <hi>promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cua venere, vagis libidinibus, Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia, quàm legitima vxore:</hi> whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,<note place="margin">Epiphan. rom. 7. lib. 1. haere. 25.</note> fornication, Sodomie, then lawfull wedlocke,<note place="margin">1. Timot. 4</note> albeit the one be commanded, and the other for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden: but that yee preferre the doctrine of diuels, before the word of God, Antichriſt before Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and falſe Atheiſme before true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. For did not Chriſt make marriage the Image of his holy coniunction with his church, and gaue <hi>Peter</hi> the primacie of order among the Apoſtles that was a married man?<note place="margin">Aug. quaeſli. 27. ex vtre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que mixtu. Bellar. lib. 1. de cler. c. 18.</note> And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth ther is no ſcripture that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth Miniſters marriage.<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelph.</note> Yea reuerend <hi>Ignatius</hi> wiſhed to be found worthy to walke in the ſteps of the ſaints, namely of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Ioſeph, Iſaias, Peter, Paul</hi> and others <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that liued in holy marriage. And proteſteth that if any profeſſor do call lawfull wedlocke and procrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of children <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: a defiling diſtaining or filthineſſe,<note place="margin">Can. 12. &amp; 13. diſt. 3. quoni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> that he hath dwelling in him the dragon that fowle Apoſtate.<note place="margin">Vliricus Epiſ. Aeneas. Siluius in ſua Germania.</note> The lawfulneſſe of which calling was proued out of the word of God in the councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb facs="tcp:14671:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>by the Synod of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople. Yea <hi>Gregorie</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Rom. 23. 1. Ioh. 5.25.</note> beholding more then 600. childrens heads drawne out of a Fiſhpond, with blubbered cheekes condemned his decree of ſingle life,<note place="margin">Aug. doct. Chriſt. 3. cap. 7. Hierom ad Ripar. preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byt.</note> ſaying: <hi>melius eſt nubere quàm vrere:</hi> and <hi>melius eſt nubere, quam mortis occaſionem praebere:</hi> It is better to marry then to buine, yea it is better to marry then to giue occaſion of murder and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Go now yee Papiſts to ſchoole vnto the Prophets, where hauing learden to diſcerne betweene the ſpirite of Chriſt and the Dragon, tell me how farre you are from Atheiſme. Doe you not pray vnto reliques, and ſay vnto the croſſe <hi>ſalue ſancta crux:</hi> all haile holye croſſe, and vnto the Napkin <hi>Sancte ſudari or apro nobis, et ſudarium Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti
<pb facs="tcp:14671:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>libert nos a peſti et morte triſti,</hi> ô holy Napkin pray for vs, deliuer vs from the peſtilence and euil death. If Atheiſme had not poſſeſſed you,<note place="margin">Sutliu us de eccl. Cath. Their ſilken garments kept at Rome are of the Italian faſhion.</note> how dare you call your couſning traſh, ſacred &amp; holy reliques? Elſe muſt <hi>Peter</hi> &amp; the ſanits be mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſters, <hi>Ioſepth</hi> &amp; <hi>Mary</hi> be <hi>Italians,</hi> &amp; Chriſt borne out of <hi>Bethleem.</hi> Howbeit the <hi>Valentinians</hi> were heretiques that worſhipped the croſſe: and do not the papiſts ſo? the <hi>Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratians</hi> were heretiques,<note place="margin">Irenaeus lib. 1 Aug. hereſ. 7.</note> &amp;c. ſo was <hi>Marceline</hi> too, they for worſhiping the Images of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> and ſhe of <hi>Ieſus</hi> and <hi>Paule:</hi> and do not the Papiſts ſo?<note place="margin">Bell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. lib. 1. c. 13. de ſanct. beat.</note> The <hi>Collyridians</hi> were here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques for worſhipping the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> and do not the papiſts ſo? yea muſt not euery country, citie, towne,<note place="margin">Epiphan. li. 3. haerel. 79. Lactant. de vero cult. cap. 17.</note> village, company, trade, occupation, and perſon, haue their Saint to worſhip by popiſh inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And were not the <hi>Angelici</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>heretiques, becauſe they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the Angels?<note place="margin">Iraeneus lib. 2 c. 59. Aug. haer. 39 Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Annot. Apoc. 3</note> yet the papiſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend and maintaine the ſelfe ſame adoration againſt the ſcripture. Would you know where to finde <hi>Pelagianiſme?</hi> then haue recourſe to popery. That will teach you a man may be perfect in this life,<note place="margin">Aug. haer. 88.</note> and keepe all the commandements, as was <hi>Franciſcus</hi> that kept the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell at an inch,<note place="margin">Rhem. 5. Ioh. 5 ſect. 1. lib. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormitat.</note> 
               <hi>non tranſgreſſus vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> apicem aut iotam:</hi> and failed not in any title: in whome were all the vertues of all the Saints in all the Bible <hi>vnitiuè et coniunctiuè,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Con. Trid. ſeſ. 6. cap. 18. Conc. Trid. ſeſ. 5. cap. 1. de pecc. orig.</note> gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together and abiding. That wil tell you there remaines no origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſinne in the faithfull,<note place="margin">Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Annot. Rom. 6.8.12 Sixius 4.ccc. Trid. cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſ. Rom.</note> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence in the regenerate is no ſinne, nor againſt the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.<note place="margin">Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Annot. Luk. 5.1. 2. Cor. 5.10.</note> That the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceiued without ſinne; that righteouſneſſe may be obtained by the law. And that ſome are ſo iuſt
<pb facs="tcp:14671:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>in this life,<note place="margin">Lyranns li. 3 cap. 19. Hiero<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueri. Pelag. lib. 2. Epheſ. 2.3.</note> as they need no repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: let <hi>Hierom, Auguſtine,</hi> yea <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Apoſtles affirme, and proue the contrary neuer ſo ſoundly. But it may be that theſe <hi>Cathariſts</hi> will lend ſome eare vnto their popiſh pillars.<note place="margin">4. Heb. 3. Galat. Aug. haereſ. 38.</note> If ſo, who ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed the ſcholemen your famous founders of <hi>Pellagiàniſme,</hi> as men oppoſite to the conſtant currant of the Fathers? euen your faithfull <hi>Roffenſis,</hi> who conuicted <hi>Pighius</hi> your gallant Champion of <hi>Pella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianiſme?</hi> euen your valiant <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus Soto:</hi> yet <hi>Ruardus Tapperu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> leaning vpon that broken ſtaffe the <hi>Tridentine</hi> councell,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. Soto de nar. &amp; grat. lib. 1. cap. 9. Tom. 2. art. 8. Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Trid. ſeſſ. 5. c 7. Luſitan Liri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſ. de quad. iuſt. lib. 1. c. 7. et cap. 25. Protoc. Fran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. art. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Conc. Trid ſeſſ. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct. 5.</note> doth all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmeare and mudde himſelfe in this hereſie: But for all his <hi>Louinian</hi> Deaneſhip, <hi>Lirenſis,</hi> a man of his owne ſtampe, is bolde to brand both him, and confeſſor <hi>Soto</hi> with <hi>Pellagianiſme.</hi> Which infectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath ſo feſtred in the intrals of papiſtry,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>as ſometime it breaths out Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,<note place="margin">Aug. haer. 69. &amp; cont. lit. Petil.</note> ſometimes leſlenning the crime of originall ſinne, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times denying it to be ſinne at all. Now including the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the bounds of papiſtry;<note place="margin">Theod. hiſt. lib. 1. cap. 19.</note> &amp; then excluding all that follow not the Pope. Sometimes flying,<note place="margin">6. Math. 1. Tim. 4. Aug. haer. 46 Euſcb. hiſt. 15. cap. 16. &amp; 17. &amp;c.</note> &amp; reſiſting the authoritie of the Magiſtrate, and ſometimes denying him any medling or dealing with Church affaires: yea ſometimes hauing their ſtabbers, poyſoners, &amp; priuie murderers: as they had of the Prince of <hi>Condy,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onie, Ioanna</hi> of <hi>Nauarre,</hi> and many other. O returne yee Prince mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, &amp; people killing Atheiſts, conſider your teaching, which Chriſt calles hypocriſie, and Saint <hi>Paule</hi> the doctrine of diuels. You think to merit heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by abſtaining with the <hi>Manichie</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fleſh, milke,<note place="margin">Blondus. Plo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinà. Eckius. Aug. cont. Fauſt. Man. lib. 19. ca. 22.</note> cheeſe &amp; egges, &amp; feare you not to
<pb facs="tcp:14671:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>merite hell by ſoothing men in murder and adultery? If <hi>Montanus</hi> made lawes in compelling men to faſt, you will maintaine with fire <hi>Theoleſphorus</hi> Lent, <hi>Calixtus</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring dayes, <hi>Leos</hi> Friday, and <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories</hi> Saturday.<note place="margin">Philip Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaeus.</note> Let the <hi>Maniches</hi> ſweare neuer ſo faſt <hi>per creatur as</hi> by the creatures: you will not be wanting to the Saints. Yea no oath muſt be ſo deare and holy as that, which is vſed by the bones and re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of the dead. Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing if you in very truth defie that masked Atheiſme,<note place="margin">Aug. haer. 50. Rhem. Anot. Acies. 17.29. Theo. baeret. fab. lib. 4.</note> why defend you the hereſie of the <hi>Anthropomorphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> painting God in your churches like an aged man? But indeed <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> his practiſe is your beſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, <hi>Qui magis chriſtianus videba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quàm erat:</hi> you will make ſhew of that you neuer meane.<note place="margin">Aug. haereſ. 68.</note> Euen your Ieſuites that carry the name of Ieſus, will ſildome practiſe the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>workes of Chriſt. It may be you affect with <hi>Neſtorius</hi> a kinde of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie, and diſſemble continencie with a wan countenance, and a pale looke, but the more cloſely to inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate your ſelues into Ladies com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and womens cloſſets. For you are deuoted men: barefoote <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lagellants</hi> and <hi>Franciſcants,</hi> your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ownes ſhauen, cowles graye,<note place="margin">Biel. ſup. 4. diſt. 16. q. 4. prop. 1. Aug. haereſ. 57.</note> and girdels muſt be full of knots: you wil obſerue your canonical houres but not labour in any caſe, leaſt you ſhould tranſgreſſe the precepts of the <hi>Euchites.</hi> To eate fleſh and be married an horrible thing among <hi>Carthuſians:</hi> to touch money were to defile the <hi>Minorits:</hi> and to haue poſſeſſions were to tranſgreſſe the conſtitutions of <hi>Benedictus</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minicus:</hi> yea and not to follow the Apoſtate <hi>Iulian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oreg. Nazin. orat. 1. cor. Agrip. de van. ſcient.</note> albeit they carry the bag with <hi>Iudas.</hi> If they vow,<note place="margin">Epiphan. haereſ. 61.</note> it muſt not be broken be it neuer ſo
<pb facs="tcp:14671:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>vngodly, and vnlawfull: put caſe they vowe virginitie,<note place="margin">Thom. 1. quod liber. q. 15. Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. Holco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n ſap. cap. 2. lcct. 24. Rhem. Amot. 1. Cor. 7.28.</note> and cannot keepe it, to marry were to diſſent from the Apoſtolicke hereticke, without a diſpenſation from the Pope, for he onely may diſpence with marriage.<note place="margin">M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yr. in. cron. Fland.</note> It is no ſinne to make ſtewes of their Nunneries, and dennes for <hi>Sodomie</hi> of their Monaſteries.<note place="margin">Sabell. volater Polydor.</note> And although they reueale it in confeſſion, yet <hi>iura periura ſecretum prodere noli:</hi> they haue learnde a trick or two of <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilianiſme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Arno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. Bri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſ. Grunth. lib. 3. Stibilius.</note> be it murder or treaſon, yea againſt the Pope himſelfe, they muſt not diſcloſe it. But if it come to paſſe,<note place="margin">Aug. haereſ. 70. Caictam tom. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>act. 2.</note> we confute theſe Athei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall conceits from the worde of God, they can appeale to counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feite traditions,<note place="margin">Aug. haereſ. 70.</note> and call them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities,<note place="margin">Rhem. Annot. 1 chef. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cct. 2.</note> and with the <hi>Priſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clianiſt</hi> equall Apocrypha with ſcripture: and for a ſhift make more wordes of God then the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.
<pb facs="tcp:14671:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>For if the Paſtors teach it,<note place="margin">Deut. 4.2. &amp; 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.32. Prou. 30.6. Apoc. 22.18.</note> be it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>euer ſo beſide the ſcripture, yet it is to be taken for the word of God, and if Chriſt the ſonne of God his Prophets &amp; Apoſtles interdict &amp; forbid ſuch ſcripture coyning, and ſeale it with a ſearefull cureſe: then can the Pope create a new Chriſt, ſaying: <hi>qui creauit me dedit mihi cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>are ſe:</hi> &amp; he that made me without my ſelfe,<note place="margin">Gal. Biel. lcct. 4. in expol. can. miſſae.</note> is made of me be my ſelf. Wherfore if they deſtroy his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall body,<note place="margin">6. Iohn.</note> borne of the Virgin <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> they can make him another bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die created by the Prieſt, elſe you might eſteeme them as blockiſh as the groſſe <hi>Capernaites,</hi> that ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the fleſh, bone, and blood of Chriſt, as he was borne of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin ſhould be torne in peeces with their teeth. And why not (ſaith their Angelicall Maſter) is not <hi>hoc,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. part. 3. q. 75. art. 5.</note>
               <hi>quod conficimus, corpus ex virgine:</hi> which is made in the conſecration
<pb facs="tcp:14671:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>the body that was borne of the virgin <hi>Mary?</hi> No ſaith <hi>Harding,</hi> it is no viſible and mortall body, but a glorified, immortall, impaſſible, &amp; ſpirituall body. It is <hi>Corpus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Biell) tale non tantum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biel. lib. 4. diſt. 11. q. 1.</note> 
               <hi>quia non eſt in ſacramente quantum:</hi> a body but without quantitie: Not ſo (ſaith <hi>Gardiner</hi>) the parts be diſtinct one from another.<note place="margin">Gard. lib. 3.</note> Yea ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 3. de Euchariſt. cap. 7.</note> the body of Chriſt is in the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with all his parts and dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.<note place="margin">Alex. Halespert. 4. q. 25. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. 1 Gloſt. can. qui bene non cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diunt de concep. diſt. 2. Bellar. lib. 3. cap. 24.</note> For (ſaith <hi>Hales</hi>) if a Dog or Hog chance to eate it, <hi>traijcitur in ventrem,</hi> it paſſeth into their belly. Not ſo ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> but if a Mouſe do chance to eate it, it cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to be Chriſt his body. And good reaſon ſaith <hi>Caietan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caiet. tom. 2. tract. 2. cap. 3.</note> for <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tualiter, et non percipiendo, ſed cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo ſumitur corpus Chriſti:</hi> Chriſt his body is eaten ſpiritually by faith, not carnally with the mouth. What then is it which nouriſheth
<pb facs="tcp:14671:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>he body?<note place="margin">Harding. apoll.</note> The accidents ſaith <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</hi> For the accidents ſaith <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine,</hi> are eaten with the teeth: But where then is Chriſt his body? In heauen ſaith <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. 3. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. cap. 22.</note> and at the ſame time on earth. Fie, fie, what a ſtirre is here contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, impoſſibilities, vntrothes,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 3. cap. 4.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon, religion, &amp; the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without any ſmacke of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme. Very like that Atheiſme muſt be packing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome, where Antichriſt ſwayes the ſcepter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing oppoſite to Chriſt, an enemie to the Goſpell and an aduerſary to true religion. What?<note place="margin">Apoc. 17. Aug. ciuit. 18. cap. 22</note> is the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt without a God? why, is the ſonne without the father, the wife without an huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, a lining body without an head,<note place="margin">2. Theſſal. 2.</note> and chriſtianitie without Chriſt? but is Popery the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Antichriſt, Rome the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis or chiefe city of his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>and the Pope the captain generall of this armie?<note place="margin">2. Theſſal. 2.</note> yea if this be that Apoſtate kingdome, whoſe Prince is without controulement exalting himſelfe aboue all that is God, and not regarding the God of his fathers.<note place="margin">11. Dan.</note> But the Pope maketh lawes to binde the conſcience, and executeth with more ſeuerity the breaking of his popiſh precepts,<note place="margin">Diſt. 40. ſi papa.</note> then the tranſgreſſion of the Lords commandement: He can make new gods: ſet up Idols, and deny Ieſus to be Chriſt. He can counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit the Lambe, yet ſpeake like the Dragon: ſet in the temple, but to vndermine Chriſt: profeſſe reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uerthrow the goſpell compute the time, deſcribe the place, note the workemen, marke the building, &amp; conſider the whole proceeding of his kingdome, and you wil ſay the Pope is Antichriſt.<note place="margin">17. Apoc.</note> The place which <hi>Iohn</hi> calleth <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. ant. Iudae Hieror. Eſa. 47. Aug. ciuit. 18. Orol. lib. 18. 3. Blondus.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>is by the Fathers conſtrued to be <hi>Rome,</hi> for her ſituation, her go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erment, her type, her reſort, her behauiour, and her citizens: who ſay, they are the miniſters of Chriſt out ſerue Antichriſt, euen the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of Romiſh <hi>Babylo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> that purple coulo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed whore. The time: when the imped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments are remoued,<note place="margin">Hieron Eſa. 21. Decret. 6. Bar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omil. 33. in cant.</note> the Emperors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eate tranſlated, and the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>maine</hi> Empire ouerthrowne: at what time the Pope muſt ſit in the Emperors place,<note place="margin">Hieron. prolog. de ſpiritu. ſanct.</note> free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vniues fall Biſhop, Chriſt his vicar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruling with two ſwords,<note place="margin">Apoc. 13. can. nemini. 17. q. 3. can. ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 0. q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Greg. Epiſt. 7.3.8.78.79. Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag. ſeſſ. 1. diſt. 21. Gratian. can. ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor diſt. 96.</note> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Emperors to kiſſe his feete, boaſting himſelfe to be God, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped of men; ſubiecting pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, diſpoſing kingdomes, ſuperior to generall councels, &amp; free gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all Chriſt his church. And now hee may diſpence with the lawes of Chriſt, alter the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſupplant all religion:
<pb facs="tcp:14671:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>for <hi>neminis eſt de ſedis Apoſtolicae iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicio iudicare:</hi> his worde muſt go before the Goſpell.<note place="margin">Dam. 4.2. c. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trau. de maior. &amp; obed.</note> His worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Maſſemongers,<note place="margin">Can. cunct. 9. q. 3. Can. ſunt qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam. 25. Q. can. ſi papa. diſt. 4.</note> Iuglers, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king wonders, faining miracles, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducers, Ieſuites, Fryers, Monkes, Dominicks, Franciſcans, Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictans, &amp;c. whome thou mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt knowe ſaith <hi>Hierom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Can. n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>minis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Q. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Math. 24.2. Theſſal. 2.2. Timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> by their names and titles <hi>non eccleſiam Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti ſed Antichriſti eſſe ſynagogam:</hi> to be the ſeruants of Antichriſt. And for their calling (ſaith <hi>Procopius) ſi neque Moſes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. aduerſ. Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>an.</note> 
               <hi>neque ante eum Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archae, neque poſt eum prophetae, neque in noua lege Chriſtus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. vrſper. in paral<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copiu. that thus ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke to luli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the popes legate in Bohemia.</note> 
               <hi>neque Apoſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mendic antium ordinem inſtituerint, quis dubitet opus eſſe tenebrarune <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Diaboli?</hi> If neither <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarkes, the Prophets in the olde lawe,<note place="margin">Epiſt. ad Iuſtin coad. Iuſtin. in Nouel. antent. 131. de quaruor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anct. concil.</note> neither Chriſt nor his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the new, ordained and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed theſe orders of begging Fryars: who can doubt but it is the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>worke of darkeneſſe, and of the diuel. Yea indeed the whole build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is nothing elſe but the worke of Satan: begun by hereſie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued by diſcord, finiſhed by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, and maintained by pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>icie, as falſe apparitions of ſaints, Angels, and diuels: wonders, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, motions of Images, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite other forgeries wherof their legend maketh mention. Where now is Antichriſt, if this be not his kingdome? In the yeare 1074.<note place="margin">Nauclerus.</note> when <hi>Hildebrand</hi> was Pope, the Prieſts pronounced him to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt: <hi>qui titulo Chriſti ageret ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotium Antichriſti in Babylone:</hi> who vnder the title of Chriſt wrought the workes of Antichriſt in <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon:</hi> At this time terrible commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſchiſmes, lightnings, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, earthquakes, &amp;c. and among the reſt was ſeene a fearful Comet,<note place="margin">Naucl. Gen. 36 ex Iohan. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grauo Anglo.</note> whereof <hi>Elmerius</hi> a Monke of
<pb facs="tcp:14671:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>Malmesbury gaue this iudgments art thou come, art thou come? vnto many mothers haſt thou brought woe and ſorrow.<note place="margin">Iacob. Mayor in Chron.</note> I ſawe thee long before, but now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold thee more terrible, euen the very ruine of this land. And about this time was newes brought from <hi>Turway</hi> to the Emperor at <hi>Coleine,</hi> of a woman propheſing that Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt was then in his full courſe: which woman ſuddenly vaniſhed away, and was no more ſeene. <hi>Munſter</hi> applies the Propheſie of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> concerning Antichriſt vnto <hi>Rome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. lib. 16. Epiſt. 30. lib. 4. Epiſt. 36. &amp; 38. &amp; li. 11. Epiſt. 3. Barnard. Cant. ſerm. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Petrarch</hi> reſembleth <hi>Rome</hi> vnto <hi>Babylon:</hi> and <hi>Gregories</hi> notes of Antichriſt are verified of the Pope. <hi>Bernard</hi> called the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates Pilates: the Miniſters the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of Antichriſt: and Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Euerard</hi> decyphering by the ſcripture this man of ſinne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes at the laſt, the Pope to be
<pb facs="tcp:14671:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Antichriſt: to omit the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Wormes, Sanonarola,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auentine annal. Boior lib. 7.</note> and others. And ſhall Antichriſt bring Apoſtacie into the church, oppoſe himſelfe to Chriſt,<note place="margin">Arnoldus Hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balus. Weſſelus.</note> boaſt himſelfe to be God, counterfeit the Lambe, but ſpeake like the Dragon, &amp; yet remaine without Atheiſme? Tell me then what is Atheiſme. O ſir, to be a proteſtant is to be an Atheiſt: for he defies the Pope, preferres Chriſt before Antichriſt, truth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue falſhood, the worde before traditions, and God before Satan. Thus you make Atheiſts as you make heretiques: If a man reſiſt the vanitie, idolatrie, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your church,<note place="margin">Platina in Paulo; 2.</note> preſently he is an heretique: to eate fleſh on faſting dayes is hereſie: yea to ſay there bee Antipodes, or to ſpeake the worde <hi>Academia: vel ſerio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auentine vbi prius.</note> 
               <hi>vel ioco:</hi> in ſadneſſe or in ieſt, is hereſie.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>But if thou wilt a very little open thine eyes,<note place="margin">Rhem. Annot. Acts. 4. ſect. 2.</note> and not be obſtinate with the wicked, <hi>qui impie agent, nec intelligent:</hi> that will do wicked-lie, and will not vnderſtand,<note place="margin">Aug. de corrup. &amp; grat. cap. 14.</note> thou ſhalt plainly perceiue who is both the heretique and the Atheiſt.<note place="margin">Hieron. in Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buc. 2.</note> The Atheiſt denies Gods prouidence: and the Papiſt denies him to haue a ſtroake in all our actions: both againſt ſcripture,<note place="margin">Lumb. lib. 1. diſt. 35. ſect. 1. Specul. Pontif.</note> Fathers, and their maiſter <hi>Lumbard.</hi> The Atheiſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nics God, heauen, hell, and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie of the ſoule: ſo did not <hi>Paulus</hi> the third, who being greedy to depart to is world,<note place="margin">P. Acſquillu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Popes. Atheiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Lco 10 Alexan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Paul. 3. Benedict. 9. Iohn. 13. Clemens. 8. Greg. 7. Specula. pontif.</note> ſaid: <hi>ſe iam tria, de quibus in omni vita multum dubitaſſet experiundo cogniturum: primo an eſſet Deus; deinde an eſſent inferni aliqua ſupplicia, et deni<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> an animae eſſent immortales:</hi> that he ſhould now be aſſured of three things by experience, of which in all his life he ſtood in doubt: Firſt
<pb facs="tcp:14671:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>whether there were a God: then whether there were any torments in hell: and laſtly whether the ſoules were immortall. Neither was <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23. an Atheiſt, whom the Synode of <hi>Conſtance</hi> depriued of his Popedome, for denying the immortality of the ſoule: yet both theſe were Biſhops of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſtoph. Marcel. Concil. Later. ſect. 4.</note> The Atheiſt ſets vp other Gods beſides the maker of heauen and earth: and the Papiſts will haue the ſaints to heare our prayers, and know our thoughts.<note place="margin">Extrau. Iohn. 22. cum inter in Gloſſ.</note> But the Pope muſt be <hi>alter Deus:</hi> yea <hi>Dominus noſter Deus.</hi> our Lord God. He may iudge the ſcriptures, make Saints, forgiue ſinnes. He hath all power giuen him both in heauen and earth: He cannot erre,<note place="margin">Lib. ceren. pontif. lib. 1. fol. 735. Luitprand,</note> albeit he calleth for aide vnto the diuell when he playes at Dice, as did Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13.<note place="margin">Baleus.</note> The Atheiſt makes Chriſt an Impoſtor: and
<pb facs="tcp:14671:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth called the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell <hi>Fabulam Chriſti:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trid. concil. ſeſſ. 4. c. 8. Floſc. bear. Franc. conform. vinea. &amp;c. Bern. in Roſar.</note> a tale, and a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Yea the Papiſts make him but a Chriſt for faſhion, when as they ſet vp other mediators, and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine merits.<note place="margin">Garat de inuoc. ſanct.</note> For wherefore came <hi>Clara</hi> with <hi>Francis</hi> into the world, but to ſaue all thoſe, <hi>Quae eam inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caturae eſſent:</hi> that ſhould pray vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her? doe they not call the virgin <hi>Mary Commune propitiatorium:</hi> the common propitiatory for the whole world, and wreſt the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture from Chriſt vnto the Virgine ſaying: <hi>In te domina ſper aui: miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere mei domina: dixit dominus domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae meae:</hi> I haue hoped in thee O Lady: haue mercie vpon me O Lady: the Lord ſaid vnto my La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſet thou on my right hand?<note place="margin">Ladies pſalter.</note> &amp;c. And no meruell, for when the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell in a certaine maide would not be moued with prayers made vnto the Father,<note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>engrious.</note> Sonne, and holy
<pb facs="tcp:14671:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ghoſt,<note place="margin">Bonauentura Ladies pſalter. Pſal. 41.10.</note> 
               <hi>Caniſius</hi> laying the image of <hi>Mary</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the head of the poſſeſſed, forthwith the diuell cryed out: <hi>O mulier quid me calcas, &amp; caput me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um conteris;</hi> ô woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> why doſt thou ſpurne me and breake my head? Wherfore they ſing vnto her <hi>Aue maris ſtella,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hym. Eccleſ. poſt pſalmos Dauidis a G. Genebrardo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ornatos.</note> &amp; ſo forth as followeth in that blaſphemous himne. Theſe are they that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew vs a new way to heauen withoùt Chriſt, and yet be voide of Atheiſme: as by <hi>Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horae. ad vſum Sarum. In pontifical. lib. 1. ſect. 7.</note>
               <hi>Vincentius, Gregory, Petronella, Thomas Becket, Agnus dei, Angels, Images, workes &amp; indulgences.</hi> Who affirmed the Philoſophers might be ſaued without Chriſt?<note place="margin">Andrat. lib. 3.</note> Papiſts.<note place="margin">Scotus prolog. ſent. c. vnum extr. de maior &amp; obed.</note> Who depriues Chriſt of his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood? papiſts. Yea who diſgrades him of all his offices? papiſts. Who makes new articles of ſaluation?<note place="margin">C. 1. de conſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudi. Gloſſ. in c. ſect. diſt. 34. &amp;. c. preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yt. diſt. 82.16. Q. 1. quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque in gloſſ.</note> papiſts. Who can diſpence againſt the Apoſtles, the new teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, the law of nature, and the law of God? Papiſts. Yea who denies Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>his Church, and the Church her Chriſt? Papiſts.</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt will play of all ſides: with <hi>Elias</hi> worſhip <hi>Iehouah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kings. 18.</note> and and with <hi>Iezabel</hi> offer ſacrifice to <hi>Baal:</hi> with <hi>Sidrac,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Dan.</note> 
               <hi>Meſhach,</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> honor the God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; with <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the golden Image.<note place="margin">2. Math.</note> Seeke Chriſt with the wiſe men, goe to worſhip the childe with <hi>Herod.</hi> In ſhew a Proteſtant, but in truth a Papiſt. For who indeauor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile religions, to be mediators betweene God and Mammon, truth and falſehoods, proteſtants and papiſts? falſe ſurnamed Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholickes.<note place="margin">Philaſt, Brir. Epiſc. in cant. haereſ.</note> Who are thoſe that with <hi>Rhetorius</hi> affirme all hereticks <hi>rectè ambulare, et rectè dicere:</hi> walke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and ſpeake the truth?<note place="margin">The treatiſe made in Paris tending to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification.</note> That make treatiſes tending to Pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſay, the Popiſh religion is true as they take the word: and
<pb facs="tcp:14671:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the <hi>Hugonites</hi> true as they vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the ſcripture? euen profeſſed members of the <hi>Romaine</hi> Church. Is not this to make a felowſhip of righteouſneſſe, with vnrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: a communion of light and darkeneſſe;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 6.14.</note> a concorde betweene Chriſt and <hi>Beliall:</hi> and religion a compoſition of hereſies? whereas <hi>Clemens</hi> reports thus of heretickes, that <hi>Magis impij ſunt quàm Indaei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Clemens in Conſtitution.</note> 
               <hi>et magis ſine Deo quàm Gentiles:</hi> more wicked then the Iewes, and more without God then the Gentiles. And God ſpeakes thus of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dicean</hi> Church; becauſe thou art luke-warme, and neither colde nor hotte, it will come to paſſe that I ſhall ſpew thee out of my mouth.<note place="margin">3. Apoc 16.</note> Take heed then of <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the Philoſopher, that would perſwade <hi>Valens</hi> the Emperor <hi>Deo gratam eſſe ſectarum varietatem, vt it a pluri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus modis colatur:</hi> that God was
<pb facs="tcp:14671:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>well pleaſed with varieties of ſects, becauſe by that meanes he may haue more ſundry and diuerſe wayes of his worſhip and ſeruice.<note place="margin">Homer Odyſſ.</note> And beware of thoſe changelings,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 8. cap. 30. Ariſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hiſt. 9.6</note> and Camelions: that can <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> diſſemble very profoundly: vſe the ſhepheards voice with the <hi>Hiena,</hi> but to deſtroy the dog, and caſt forth ſweet ſauoures with the Panther, but to deuoure the beaſts. For they are like the <hi>Remora</hi> hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the courſe of religion; and like thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> falſe bretheren,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Galat.</note> that entered the church of <hi>Galatia:</hi> yea rather do as the Lord your God commaunded you,<note place="margin">5. Deut. 32.</note> and turne not aſide to the right hand, nor to the leſt.</p>
            <p>The Atheiſt to deſtroy religion,<note place="margin">Apolog. c. 1. ſect. 3.</note> will mainteine and eſtabliſh all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions: and the Pope for money will diſpence with all religions: yea many religions muſt be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed
<pb facs="tcp:14671:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>in one commonwealth, that conſcience may be free, and Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh catholiques may haue liberty;<note place="margin">32. Exod. 3. King. 18.</note> yet <hi>Moſes</hi> could not ſuffer the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Calfe in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> nor <hi>Elias Baal,</hi> and God to be worſhipped in one common-wealth;<note place="margin">16. Pſal.</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> would not offer the offrings of blood;<note place="margin">2. Macab. 6.24</note> nor <hi>Eleazarus</hi> diſſemble to eate Swines fleſh againſt the law; The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> muſt haue continuall war with the <hi>Amalekites;</hi>
               <note place="margin">25. Numb.</note> and <hi>Phinees</hi> was highly commended for killing the <hi>Iſraelite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">21. Geneſ.</note> that was coupled with a woman of <hi>Madian:</hi> For there is but one faith,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 5.10. Leu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</note> one baptiſme, one God, one Chriſt, one Church,<note place="margin">Tertul. de caro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> militis.</note> and ſhe no ſtrumpet to receiue all commers: the Lyon and the Lambe cannot hoorde in one fowlde: <hi>Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Iſmael</hi> in one houſe;<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.2. Chron. 16.2. Chron. 18.1. Cor. 1.13.2. Timot. 4.5</note> the Arke, and <hi>Dagon,</hi> in one church; holy and prophane fire in one cenſer; Chriſt and
<pb facs="tcp:14671:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Antichriſt in one temple.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 3. cap. 62. Socrat. lib. 5. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Non bene connénit ſigno Chriſti et ſigno diaboli, caſtris lucis, et caſtris tenebrarum: non poteſt vna anima duobus deberi:</hi> and yee cannot drinke the cuppe of Chriſt and of Diuels. What pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked Gods anger againſt <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Aſa, Amaſia,</hi> and <hi>Iohoſaphat?</hi> the permiſſion of more religions in one kingdome: Chriſt muſt not be deuided, and <hi>Timothy</hi> muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of <hi>Alexander: Conſtantine</hi> ouerthrew the temples of the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retiques; and <hi>Iouinian</hi> denied to be their Emperor, that were diſciples vnto <hi>Iulian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Kings. 21. Amb. Epiſt. 5. Orat. cont. Auxent.</note> 
               <hi>Naboth</hi> defended his Vine with his blood; and <hi>Ambroſe</hi> choſe rather to dye, then to yeelde one of his churches to the <hi>Arrians.</hi> But to ſet vp more religions in a kingdome, is to bring peace vnto the countrie? very like, ſuch peace as <hi>Simons</hi> Horſe brought vnto <hi>Troy: Aeneas</hi> ſword vnto <hi>Dido,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>and <hi>Deianira</hi> her ſhirt vnto <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> Brought not the ſuffering of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>Arrian</hi> great peace vnto the world, that had almoſt euerted Chriſt and chriſtendome?<note place="margin">Hiero. Epiſt. 62</note> 
               <hi>Nihil <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rande eſt pacem voce pretendere, et <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>pere deſiruere, verbis ſomniare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ordiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Euſeb. hiſt. 4. cap. 14.</note>
               <hi>re exigere ſeruitutem: Iohn</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Apoſtle fled from <hi>Cerinthus, Ne balneae ipſae corruant:</hi> ſuppoſing the place could not long endure, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat contained an enemie vnto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruth; And <hi>Polycarpus</hi> would not companie with <hi>Marrian</hi> that was <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rimogenitum diaboli,</hi> the childe of Satan. May a man carry fire in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſome, &amp; not burne his clothes? and walke vpon hoat coales, and not ſcorch his feete? may a man ſuffer the plague in his houſe, and not infect his family? a Woolfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his Lambes; and not hurt his fowld? and a ſerpent in the cradle, and not ſpoile his childe?
<pb facs="tcp:14671:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>But ſuch is hereſie,<note place="margin">Cyprian. Epiſt. 20.</note> and falſe religi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on to the church and common<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wealth: euen a plague that pierce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the hart: an ague that brings deat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eternall: a fire that burnes to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruction: and a ſerpent that ſting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to perdition: and do not theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> men deſerue better of religion then the Atheiſt,<note place="margin">Tertul. deprae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.</note> that wiſh ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> loſſe vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">Hieron. Oſc 2.7.</note> and hurt vnto the Church?<note place="margin">Ambroſe. Epiſt. 80.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Atheiſt pretends religion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but for pollicie: ſometimes with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Herod</hi> the more eaſily to deſtroye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the infant, he alſo will go and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Chriſt: ſometimes with <hi>Simon Magus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Math.</note> the better to win credit and profit,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Actes.</note> he alſo muſt be the great<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> power of God: ſometimes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphyra</hi> to conceak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his hypocriſie: and in a worde.<note place="margin">5. Actes.</note> with this vizard to couer rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, murders, adulteries, &amp; all ſorts of villanies. And dooth this alſo
<pb facs="tcp:14671:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouch the Papiſts? witneſſe their Spaniſh Inquiſition, their holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eague; the Parliament of <hi>Prouince;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he court in <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Actes and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents.</note> called the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing chamber; and the blood of holy Martyrs, with the which <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ſere orbis infectus eſt:</hi> almoſt the whole world hath beene lately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained &amp; beſmeared. Here might you ſee dead mens bones brought to the barre, and there condemned to the fire for hereſie; here might you ſee the mother burning at the ſtake, the childe from her wombe flying the firie flames,<note place="margin">At the maſſacre in Antwerpe.</note> yet throwne againe into the middeſt thereof for an hereticke. Now might you heare a hideous noyce crying <hi>occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, trucida, occide trucida, viuat miſſa, viuat miſſa,</hi> murder, kill, ſlay, let the Maſſe liue,<note place="margin">Faelix Earle o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Wattenbr.</note> and let all ſlide. And now might you heare men ſweare, that they would ride vp to the ſpurs in the blood of the <hi>Lutherans.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Illyricus.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>If this be not ſufficient to open vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee their Satanicall natures,<note place="margin">Apoe. 12.</note> in perſecuting the ſeede of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man: then attend a little, and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhalt apparantly behold their wol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh corpes masking in ſheepe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cloathing: perſwading falſhood for chriſtian truth,<note place="margin">Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Math. 19. Math. 10.</note> and preſcribing deadly poyſon, in lewe of whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome potions to the ſlaughter o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> many a ſilly ſoule. For wherevnto belongeth the withholding of the facred ſcripture from the hungry people, which are the bleſſed food and nouriſhments of their ſoules, commaunded and practiſed by Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitiue church?<note place="margin">5. Iohn.</note> becauſe for ſooth the people being kept in ignorance (which they ſay is the mother of Piety) ſhould not eſpye their workes,<note place="margin">Chriſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. 9. Epiſt. ad colloſſ.</note> thereby to deteſt their knaueries: wherevnto appertaines their ſeruice in an vnknowne-toung,<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. fect. 22. cap. 8.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>and hiding from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the onely way vnto ſaluation,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 2. de verb. c. 16.</note> which is by Chriſt? but to ſhew their Iewiſh mindes vnto Chriſt,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.</note> and their Atheiſticall conceits vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſtianitie. When a Iew of <hi>Ratisbone</hi> conuerted to the ſaith, was demanded, why the Iewes thirſted after the blood of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, anſwered, it was a myſterie onely knowne vnto the <hi>Rabbins,</hi> and men of higheſt place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this was their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, if any of them were ready to make an end of this preſent life. a <hi>Rabbin</hi> annoynted him with blood, vſing theſe or ſuch like wordes vnto him, ſaying: If he that was promiſed in the lawe, and in the Prophets hath truly appeared,<note place="margin">Fincelius. lib. 3. de mirac.</note> and if this Ieſus crucified be the very Meſſias, then let the blood of that innocent ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that died, cleanſe thee from thy ſinnes, &amp; helpe thee
<pb facs="tcp:14671:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>to eternall life. And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports thus of the Iewes of <hi>Tiberias,</hi> that they would whiſper after this ſort in a dying mans eare: Beleeue in <hi>Ieſus</hi> of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> whome ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Princes crucified, for he ſhal come to iudge thee in the latter day: were the Iewes adu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſaries to Chriſt, and enemies to their conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cience, and doe not our Papiſts ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond them in their Atheiſme? who teach a man muſt put his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in good workes, for they merit eternall life.<note place="margin">Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, of the Biſhop of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</note> Howbeit whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Stephen Gardiner</hi> lying on his death bed heard the Biſhop of <hi>Chicheſter</hi> telling him of Gods promiſes and free iuſtification by the blood of Chriſt, he ſaid: what my Lorde will yee open that gap now? then farewell altogether: to me and ſuch other in my caſe you may ſpeake it, but open this window to the people, and then farewell alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.
<pb facs="tcp:14671:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>And ſir <hi>Chriſtopher Blunt</hi> had theſe wordes at the time of his execution: Beare witneſſe I dye a Catholicke,<note place="margin">Anno. 1600. March. 18.</note> yet ſo as I hope to be ſaued onely by the death and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſt, and by his merits, not aſcribing any thing to my owne workes: yea and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> their great <hi>Goliah</hi> after much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the truth, at the laſt giues vp his verdit,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 5. de iuſtifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. c. 7.</note> ſaying: <hi>propter periculum maius gloriae tutiſsimum eſt fiduciam totam in ſola Dei miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia et benignitate reponere:</hi> for the more aſſurance of future glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, it is the ſafeſt way to put our whole truſt and confidence, in the mercy and louing kindneſſe of Almighty God.<note place="margin">17. Luke. 9. Dan.</note> For when wee haue done all that wee can, wee are but vnprofitable ſeruants, wherefore wee pray not in our owne righteouſneſſe, but in thy manifolde mercies.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now let the Papiſt then ſpeake whether he be that blood deſiring or ſoule-deuouring Atheiſt: Pope <hi>Hildebrand,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benno Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. in vita. &amp; geſt. Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brand.</note> 
               <hi>quia diebus per paganos Chriſtum publice perſequi non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, per falſum Monachum ſub habitu Monaſtico, ſub habitu religionis nomen Chriſti fradulenter ſubuertere diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebat:</hi> becauſe he could not in publicke conueniently perſecute Chriſt, he ſought in ſecret vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the pretence of religion, deceitful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to ſubuert the name of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed.<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> The old <hi>Romaines</hi> profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed religion <hi>magis admorem, quam adrem:</hi> rather for faſhion then for truth: and more to ſatiſſie the law, then to be pleaſing vnto God. Wherefore <hi>Pontifex Sheuola</hi> ſaid, <hi>expedit falli in religione ciuitates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ang. ciuitat. 6. c. 10. &amp; lib. 4. cap. 26.</note> 
               <hi>quia non niſi homines in metu quodam et officio continendos eandem proponi cenſendum eſt:</hi> It is expedient that cities ſhould be deceiued concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:14671:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>religion, becauſe it ſerues to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o other end, but to keepe them in feare, and in their dutie. And to what other end belongs the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Indulgences and Popiſh Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but to keepe men in feare, and picke their purſes? For who doe they place in Purgatorie but the rich and wealthy men, by whome they may haue proffit and aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage by helping them out of pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,<note place="margin">Bellar. de purg. lib. 2. cap. 15. &amp; 18.</note> and praying for them that they might haue eaſe?<note place="margin">Platina.</note> Yet <hi>Harding</hi> ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called it <hi>purgatorij pictas flam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas:</hi> and <hi>Papyraceos parietes:</hi> pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted flames and paper wals. And <hi>Platina</hi> recorded, that Pope <hi>Bone-face</hi> and 8. <hi>populis et regibus terrorem potius quàm religionem incutere co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabatur:</hi> indeauoured rather to feare, and terrifie kings and people, then to inſtruct them in religion.<note place="margin">Ioh. Dubrau. hiſt. Bohem. lib. 13.1.</note> Did not the Popes Indulgences to the <hi>Bohemians, promiſe plenam
<pb facs="tcp:14671:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>condonationem delictorum:</hi> full par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of all their ſinnes, which made <hi>Iohn Huſsius</hi> depart from the ſea o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Rome?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Huſſ.</note> And <hi>Tetzelius</hi> that impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent publiſher of that traſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the people <hi>animam in coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum euolare quam primum iactu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> nummulus in ciſta tinuerit:</hi> the ſoule ſhould flye to heauen, ſo ſoone as the money gingled in the box, which made <hi>Luther</hi> forſake the Pope. And good reaſon, for what is his religion, but the high way to Atheiſme, ſeeing no man will feare to ſinne, that can buy it off with a little money?<note place="margin">Taxa cancel. Apoſt. printed at Paris. 1520.</note> Hath not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, fratricide, theft, whoredome, murder, ſacriledge, patricide, and euery ſinne his price to be ſould in the Popes ſhop?<note place="margin">Lib. Tax. publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at Rome 1475.</note> An abſolution for them that carnally know their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſiſter, kinſwoman: <hi>tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quin<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">13. Rom. Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard Epiſt. 42.</note>
               <hi>groſsis eſt taxata:</hi> yea any ſinne may haue his pardon for his price. Thus
<pb facs="tcp:14671:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>may the Pope not only breake the laws of God himſelfe,<note place="margin">Chryſeſt. in Rom. hom. 23.</note> but likewiſe diſpence with others for the ſame. He will not be ſubiect to Kings &amp; Princes, nor permit his Prieſts,<note place="margin">Theod. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oph. Oecumen in Rom. lib. 4. ſent. diſt. 34.</note> and Monkes to obey the word. Yea <hi>illa praecepta quaein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ege Dei de gradibus matrimonialibus lata ſunt, Papa iure poſitiuo ſiue eccleſiaſtico immutare po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt.</hi> He may change the lawe of God, touching degrees of matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie: and now <hi>Emanuell</hi> king of <hi>Portugall</hi> may marry two ſiſters: and if the king of <hi>Naples</hi> marry his fathers ſiſter,<note place="margin">C. acſi Clerici. deiudiei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s. Vu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſleius Gronningeſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>act. de indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent.</note> 
               <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt can grant a diſpenſation: if the Prieſt &amp; cleargie men be adulterers <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pis datur à pontifice diſpenſandi fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultas:</hi> the Pope will giue the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops power to grant them diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations: yea <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. gaue the whole familie of the Cardinall of Saint <hi>Luce</hi> a diſpenſation to vſe Sodomie in Iune, Iuly, &amp; Auguſt.
<pb facs="tcp:14671:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>It may be you beholde a peece of their Atheiſticall phyſnomie, but will you ſee it wholely vnmasked? <hi>Matchiauell</hi> that politique Atheiſt ſets it downe for a principle: that <hi>Princeps,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mach. de prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cip. cap. 17.</note> 
               <hi>quum morte adficere ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem cup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, ſpecioſum aliquem pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> textum adhibere debet:</hi> The Prince muſt haue alwayes ſome probable pretence ſor his practiſe, and then he may proceed vnto his murders.<note place="margin">Dion. in Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone. Dion. in Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calla.</note> As had <hi>Nero,</hi> when he put his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to death, and <hi>Caracalla,</hi> when he killed his brother <hi>Seta:</hi> The Iewes making ſtirres and commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Indea</hi> and <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſephus lib. 4. de bello Iudaic.</note> about the time of <hi>Neroes</hi> Empery preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>religio,</hi> and <hi>inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uta maiorum,</hi> religion and ſtatutes of their aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cienters to be the cauſe of their rebellion, whereas indeed they ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for nothing leſſe then for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. <hi>Templum enim, pro cuius gloria pugnareſe dicebant, igne conſumpſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>et pertinacia ſua vrbem et eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam extrema clade deuaſtarunt:</hi> for they burned the temple for which they ſaid they tooke vp armes, and by their obſtinacie vtterly deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the citie, and the temple. And is not the Popes pretence religion, when he would achieue any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or performe any miſchife? for who ſo fulfils not the Popes mind, muſt by and by be an hereticke.<note place="margin">Volatcran.</note> What tranſlated the Empire of <hi>Conſtantinople?</hi> hereſie, as the Popes did pleaſe to call it.<note place="margin">Philip. haeret. Auno. 713.</note> And why was <hi>Philip</hi> the Emperor denounced to be an hereticke? <hi>quod ex mandato Dei Idola ex templis ſuſtuliſſet:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he tooke Idols out of the Temples, and from the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, according to Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Why was <hi>Fredericke</hi> the ſecond an heretick? for holding the wrong ſtirrop of the Pope; why was <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>France</hi> an hereticke?<note place="margin">4. Philip.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>becauſe hee would not take v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> armes againſt forraine nations,<note place="margin">Betrand. hiſt. Thol. Guido. Perpin. lib. de haereſ.</note> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the commandement of Pope <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi> the eight. How was <hi>Raim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> handled by his holineſſe,<note place="margin">Egiliard.</note> for n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> burning the <hi>Albigenſes?</hi> And w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> not religion his pretence,<note place="margin">Palmerius.</note> when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> exiled <hi>Deſiderius</hi> king of <hi>Italy,</hi> with wife and children into Lions, there to end his dayes in miſery, and his kingdome made <hi>S. Peters</hi> patrim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny?<note place="margin">Yet it was cuident Guiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es non religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſed regio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem affectare.</note> Was not religion the pretence of that infamous Maſacre of <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce,</hi> of the poyſoning of <hi>Iohn</hi> king of England by a Monke, albeit the king had farmed his crowne of the Pope? And is it not a Popiſh acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>haeriticis non eſſe fidem ſeruandam</hi> a man may breake his oath, troath, and faith, that is plighted to an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick? Religion was the pretence, wherefore <hi>Henry</hi> the third of <hi>France</hi> was killed by a diſſembling Monke Religion was the pretence
<pb facs="tcp:14671:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>why an hypocriticall Papiſt ſhot the Prince of <hi>Auris</hi> with a Gunne, after he had humbly ſaluted his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aieſtie. And is not this a Popiſh Theorem, <hi>principi proteſtanti qui ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em non ſeruat, qui prodit, qui perdit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m non delinquere?</hi> It is no ſinne to forſweare, deceiue, betray, and murder, a Prince, that is a prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Vnder this pretence two <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bins,</hi> with a croſſe in their handes procured the murdering of more then 4000. Chriſtians in <hi>Liſbon,</hi> but were publickely burned for it in <hi>Ebora,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1600.</note> at the commandement of <hi>Emanuell</hi> the king. Vnder this pretence a Gray Frier named bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ferdinand dela place</hi> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the king of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> to put ſundry Chriſtians to death cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them Apoſtates.</p>
            <p>Vnder this pretence of religion did <hi>Phocas</hi> kill <hi>Mauritius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and his children, and was
<pb facs="tcp:14671:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>abſolued both from murder and treaſon by Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> vpon this conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that as <hi>Phocas</hi> ſhould be Emperor,<note place="margin">Platina in vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Bonifac. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſo the Pope ſhould be <hi>Epiſcoporum princeps</hi> and <hi>caput eccleſiae:</hi> the prince of the Biſhops, and head of the Church: and can a Church whoſe head is the Pope, &amp; not Chriſt, be without Atheiſme,<note place="margin">Specul. Pontiſ.</note> A church that hath many heads at one time? Yea and vnder this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence did <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight <hi>Dart regna et auferre</hi> beſtow &amp; take away kingdomes,<note place="margin">Platina.</note> and gather, <hi>aurum pluſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam dici poteſt,</hi> gold without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: vnder this pretence the Pope ſent <hi>Parry,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ianuary 3. 1584.</note> to kill our bleſſed Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> promiſing him for his labor pardon of all his ſins: and calles it an holy act. Yea vnder this pretence they ſent forth ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications both againſt Prince and ſubiect, debarring the one from his dignitie, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:14671:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>from his dutie. Thus <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. excommunicated <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Burbon</hi> king of <hi>France,</hi> the fourth of that name, calling him the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced king of <hi>Nauarre:</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> Prince of <hi>Condy,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Nos illos illorun que poſteros priuamus in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuum, &amp;c.</hi> We depriue them,<note place="margin">Datum Romae apud 5. Marcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Anno. 1584. 5. idus Septemb. Anno primo noſtri pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus.</note> &amp; offices &amp;c, and then abſolues all their nobles, vaſſailes &amp; ſubiects of their oathes, allegeance, and duties in paine of exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication: And <hi>ſiquis hoc attenuare praeſumpſerit, indignatiouem omnipotentis Dei, et beatorum Petri, ac Pauli Apoſtolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eius ſe nouerit incurſurum:</hi> If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall preſume to diminiſh any whit hereof, he vndergoes the wrath and indignation of almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God, and of his bleſſed Apoſtles <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paule.</hi> Yet Pope <hi>Clemens</hi> the 5. abrogated the decree of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>the eight, and freed <hi>Phil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> king of <hi>France</hi> from the curſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thereof. And <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> was o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the contrary minde, in his Epiſtl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Auxilium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. 5. cap. 7. Ernan. con. c. 7. Aug. Epiſt. 75.</note> how be it not ſubiect to his Popiſh penalty. Thus <hi>Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> the 8. <hi>Martin</hi> the 5. <hi>Iulius</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2. ſent many thundering excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munications into <hi>France,</hi> but the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were all diſabled by the Counſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and court of <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>France.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gratian. c. ſiha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes 24. q. 3.</note> Thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> delt <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. with <hi>Frederick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ſending three Bulles to tormen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him: In the firſt accuſing him of ſacriledge, periury, lying, cruelty, patricide, and all vngodlineſſe. In the ſecond freeing all people, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,<note place="margin">Extat. apud Auentinum. in Anal. cont. brid. 2. Imperat.</note> Townes <hi>iure iurandi religione</hi> from their oathes, &amp; commandes it to be preached vnto the people. In the third, he calles him here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, beaſt, with other vilde tearmes, commanding all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an people, if they will haue God
<pb facs="tcp:14671:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o tender them, and to haue mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon their ſoules, not to fauour the Emperor, in deede, worde, or thought. Yet ſaith God, thou ſhalt not ſpeake euill of the ruler of the people.<note place="margin">2. Leuit. 22. Exod.</note> Thus delt <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. with <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. moſt miſerably <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yranizing ouer the ſilly Emperor, ſtirring vp trayterous <hi>Rodolph</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Lord and Maiſter,<note place="margin">Antoninus part. 2.</note> &amp; ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him a golden crowne with this inſcription. <hi>Petra dedit Petro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benno Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note>
               <hi>Petrus Diadama Rodolpho</hi> the rocke gaue the diadem to <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> beſtowed it vpon <hi>Rodolph:</hi> but it was the ouerthrow both of the Pope &amp; <hi>Rodolph</hi> For <hi>Zedechias</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury ſhall not go vnpuniſhed,<note place="margin">Ezechi. 17.17.18.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he diſpiſed the oath. Thus delt <hi>Paulus</hi> the 3. with <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. king of England a prince of happy memory. And his Popiſh <hi>Poole</hi> perſwaded with <hi>Charles</hi> the 5. tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported his army prepared againſt
<pb facs="tcp:14671:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Turke into England againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. becauſe the Pope be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baniſhed from hence,<note place="margin">Cardiral Poole lib. 3. ad Hen. 8.</note> here wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſparſum ſemen Turcicum.</hi> Turciſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was ſowed in the land. Thus de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Clemens</hi> the 5. with <hi>Franciſcus De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalus</hi> Duke of <hi>Venice:</hi> But it were a world to rip vp all their Bulle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and cruell treaſons. <hi>Religioſulos, pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regrinationum et votorum praetext<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> obambulantes prouincias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cornel. Agrip. de vanit ſcient.</note> 
               <hi>explorae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſecreta, ad omnium proditionum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera extractos eſſe:</hi> their Fryars, and walking mates, vnder pretence of vowes and pilgrimages, are fitte companions for all treacheries &amp; treaſons. And no maruell ſeeing it is a principle of Papiſtry: that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie oathe and vowe muſt be holy vnto the Pope; but neither vowe, nor oath vnto the Prince, but what ſhall pleaſe his Popedome. Neither are theſe Bulles and Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men hurtfull onely vnto Princes,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut alſo full of blaſphemies againſt almighty God: as is euident in the Bull of <hi>Pius Sixtus</hi> vpon the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Iubily,<note place="margin">Ex promonſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ioh. Bal. H. Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. Cornel. Agrip.</note> and in the Bull of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 9. directed to <hi>Albert Beham</hi> of <hi>Bath.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding leaſt I ſeeme to dwell o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uer-long vpon this demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: I come vnto the thundring Bull of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> roaring and breathing out his beaſtly threats againſt our gracious Soueraigne Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> thus popiſhly inſcribed. <hi>Sententiam declaratoriam contra ſereniſsimam Reginam Anglia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es ei adhaerentes haereticos. Qua etiam declar antur abſoluti omnes ſabditi à <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuramento fidelitatis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Datum. Romae a pud ſanctum Potium 5. kale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Mart. Anno. 1569.</note> 
               <hi>et quocun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> alio <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>debito, et deinceps obedientes anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate illaqueantur.</hi> A ſentence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratory againſt the moſt renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Queene of England, and all her hereticall adherents, abſoluing all her ſubiects from their oath of
<pb facs="tcp:14671:34"/>truſtineſſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>loyaltie, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer other duty, accurſing with a fearefull execration all thoſe, that ſhall yeeld vnto her any ſeruice or obedience. Beholde the fruites of <hi>Romiſh</hi> religion, periury, treaſon, diſobedience, and vilde reuiling of the Lords annointed, calling her <hi>ſerua vitiorum:</hi> the woman ſeruant of vice and wickedneſſe. And why? becauſe ſhe yoaked not her ſelfe vnto his Popeſhip: held not his ſtirrup with <hi>Ludouicke.</hi> yeelded not her necke with <hi>Fredericke:</hi> nor gaue him homage paying a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred markes a yeare with <hi>Richard:</hi> therfore ſhe is a prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced Queene,<note place="margin">Anno. 1569.</note> and muſt be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municated, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, diſherited, and what not. Now muſt <hi>D. Morton</hi> ſtir vp the Engliſh Catholicks to rebellion, and raiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>motions in the Noth now muſt auriculer confeſſion caſt the anker of conſpiracy: and the traterous
<pb facs="tcp:14671:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Ieſuites</hi> lay their bloody handes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lordes anoynted a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full progeny iſſuing from a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering ſpaniſh ſouldier <hi>Ignatius de Laiola.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceden. Niceph. 13. c. 34.</note> Yet thus delt not the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church with <hi>Conſtantius,</hi> and <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> albeit both atached of hereſie, the one with Eutichiſme, and the other with Arrianiſme. But what thinke our moderne Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, of this Antichriſtian Bull? Firſt they demaund <hi>An catholici non teneantur virtute Bullae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra eam arma ſumere,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theſe &amp; many more Articles of the ſame ſort were found and taken in the ſearch for Dauid Engle field in York eſhire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; recorded there in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> cell: intituled Ad conſolatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem &amp; inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Angloru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> catholicorum &amp; confeſſariorum.</note> 
               <hi>eam depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere, incarcerare, vel occidere da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta opertun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ate et victoriae conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quendae probabilitate,</hi> &amp;c. Whether the Catholickes are not bound by the ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue of that Bull to take vp armes againſt her Maieſty, to depoſe, impriſon or kilher, if opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity ſerue, or if there be any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of the victory: vnto which is anſwered: non <hi>teneri niſi,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb facs="tcp:14671:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>They are not ſimply bound there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto by the vertue of the Bull, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the matter be ſo handled, as they may be aſſured of the victory: and in that caſe, all are bound to doe their vttermoſt for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of faith and religion. Secondly they demaund <hi>An ſtante Bulla in virtute priuatus poſsit eam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> occidere:</hi> whether it be lawfull for a priuate man to kill her by the vertue of the Bull: To which it is anſwered: It is lawfull out of doubt,<note place="margin">Papiſts are no traytors.</note> if he be ſure by that meanes to deliuer the kingdome from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion. Thirdly <hi>An Catholici, &amp;c.</hi> whether the Catholicke may take an oath that <hi>Elizabeth</hi> is the true Queene of England. To this after ſome demurre is anſwered, albei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they muſt not ſweare falſely: yet they may hide, and couer the truth with any kinde of aequiuocation or doubling, eſpecially if the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandes
<pb facs="tcp:14671:35"/>be not according to lawe,<note place="margin">Bulla quatenus ſpectat ad fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem religionis &amp; catholicorum efficax &amp; inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grum man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or before a lawfull Iudge: As if it be demanded whether ſhe be the true Queene, it is enough for their oath if they vnderſtand it, that ſo indeed the common people take her, or her adherents or after any other ſort. Fourthly <hi>An Catholici,</hi> &amp;c. Whether the Catholickes for all their oath may by the vertue of the Bull take vp armes againſt her Maieſtie vpon any oportunitie: wherevnto they anſwer,<note place="margin">Baſil. Yet God accepts of the oath according to his meaning that giues the oath, or as he vnderſtands it to whome we ſweare.</note> they may do it in the caſe of religion: yea although there were no Bull, yet it is lawfull to ouerthrow &amp; thruſt a tyrant from the throne. Laſtly (to omit the reſt) <hi>An princeps ant regina ipſa excommunicata,</hi> &amp;c. Whether the Queene being excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and denounced an heretick, ſhe be alſo depriued of the right &amp; ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the kingdome, &amp; the people freed from their oath &amp; allegiance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>To which is anſwered affirmatiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,<note place="margin">Yet all the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in the world are not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince her Grace of any hereſie or tyrannie.</note> adding moreouer, that the Queene of England not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe is a heretick and a tyrant, but alſo becauſe ſhe rules with the hurt, loſſe, dammage, and diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of the whole Church of England, may be lawfully thrown from her kingdome, had there bin no bull publiſhed againſt her. Beholde how they make the lawes of God of none effect: <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurare, fallere, diſsimulare:</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare,<note place="margin">Mach. com. 2. cap. 13.</note> diſſemble, and deceaue is a commaundement of their good Lord <hi>Machiauell:</hi> If they be ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned before heretickes, <hi>ſophiſticè iurare et ſophiſticè reſpondere:</hi> to ſweare deceitfully and to anſwere Sophiſtically is authorized by their Canons.<note place="margin">Int. qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. ad tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal. iudicis pertinentes Q. 2. quomodo reſpond. in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunali haeret.</note> Indeede the heretickes called <hi>Henriciani</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolici, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramenta nec licita probarunt, nec pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ier are dubitarunt,</hi> neither allowed
<pb facs="tcp:14671:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>bathes as lawfull, nor made any queſtion to breake them, or to be forſworne.<note place="margin">2. Luke.</note> Chriſt bids vs indure with patience: the Pope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandes to reſiſt with violence.<note place="margin">1. pet. 3.2. 3. Colo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 2. Titus. Iude.</note> S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith honor the king: be ſubiect ſaith S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and ſpeake not euill of thoſe that are in authority is the concord of the ſcripture: curſe not the king ſaith the wiſeman: pray for kings ſaith the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">10. Eccleſ. 1. Timoth. 1. 1. Tim. 2. 2. Math.</note> and giue to <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is <hi>Caeſars</hi> ſaith Chriſt. <hi>Colimus imperatorem vt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem à Deo ſecundum,</hi> we reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence the Emperor as one next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God ſaith <hi>Tertullian.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. ad Scap. Tertul. Apol.</note> Chriſtians prayed for the Emperor in the primitiue Church, and were no rebells: yea it was the poeſie of the Elder Church <hi>malumus occidi quàm occidere,</hi> we had rather be killed, then kil.<note place="margin">Aug. de morib. eccleſ. catho. lib. 1. c. 30.</note> 
               <hi>Catholica eccleſia docet popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los vt ſe ſubda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t regibus:</hi> the catholick Church teacheth the people to be
<pb facs="tcp:14671:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſubiect vnto Kings: and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.<note place="margin">Can. Apoſt. 83.</note> If any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile the King, or diſhonor the Maieſtrate, if hee be a Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, he muſt be depoſed, or if a lay man, excommunicated. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinus, Valens, Valentinian</hi> the younger, <hi>Anaſtaſius, Iuſtinian, Her aclius, Iuſtinian</hi> the fourth were hereticall Princes, &amp; <hi>Iulian</hi> was an Apoſtate, yet the church of Chriſt indured,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 124.</note> ſerued and obeyed them: <hi>milites Chriſtiani, ſeruierunt Imper a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tori infideli. Dauid</hi> would neither kill <hi>Saule,</hi> nor ſuffer any of his ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to lay their handes vpon the Lords anoynted.<note place="margin">1 Sam. 16. 1. Sam. 22. 1. Sam. 24. 1. Sam. 26. Aug. cont. lit. Perili. lib. 2. cap. 48.</note> 
               <hi>Ecce Saul non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebat innocentiam, et tamen habebat ſanctitatem non vitae fed vnctionis:</hi> Yet <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man of God. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>naricus</hi> king of <hi>Gothes,</hi> when he came to viſite <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror ſaid: <hi>ſine dubio Deus terre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus
<pb facs="tcp:14671:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>eſt Imperator,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baul us Diacon de geſt. Rom. lib. 1.</note> 
               <hi>contra quem qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque manus leuare miſſus fuerit ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe ſui ſanguinis reus extitit:</hi> out of doubt the Emperor is another God on earth, againſt whome who ſo ſhall ſeeme to liſt vp his hands, is guilty of his owne bloud and deſtruction. Yet <hi>Athanaricus</hi> was an heathen.<note place="margin">D. Allen lib. of the defence of Catholickes 8. Iohn. Walden Cont. Wicleu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtas lib. 2. 5. Prou. 17. Deut. 1. Sam. 9. 1. King. 12. 1. King. 17.</note> But the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> both againſt the ſcripture, nature, religion, and all antiquity allow the murdering of Princes: an eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ſigne who is their father. The Papiſts ſay kings raigne by the Pope: but the ſcripture ſaith they rule by God. And he that reſiſtes the king withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des the ordinance of God. <hi>Ieroboham</hi> was an Idolater, yet none of the Prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded any of the people to kill him. <hi>Ahab</hi> was an Idolater, yet <hi>Elias</hi> ſeekes no inſurrection. <hi>Ieremy</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Zedechias, Daniel</hi> vnder <hi>Nabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chodonoſer, Chriſt</hi> vnder <hi>Pilate, Iohn</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>vnder <hi>Herod, Paule</hi> vnder <hi>Faelix,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> vnder <hi>Nero</hi> line, yet moue not the people to rebellion. But the Papiſts haue beene the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors almoſt of all the warres euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and diſſentions, that haue happened for the ſpace of 700. yeares in diſturbed Chriſtendom. <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſecond, <hi>Gregory</hi> the third, and <hi>Leo</hi> the third made <hi>Italy</hi> decline from their ſoueraigne Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror. <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt ſet the Frenchmen againſt the <hi>Lombardes,</hi> and maintained <hi>Pippins</hi> rebellions againſt king <hi>Childerick.</hi> Were they not Popes that ſet the <hi>Fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch</hi> &amp; <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> at oddes, that held war them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues againſt <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. &amp; the 5. <hi>Fredericke</hi> the firſt, and the ſecond <hi>Ludouick Bauarus:</hi> and ſuggeſted o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to do the like? Were they not Popes that diſturbed <hi>Naples</hi> &amp; <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon?</hi> ſowed diſcorde betweene <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>Greekes</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:14671:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Normans: England</hi> &amp; <hi>Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: France</hi> and <hi>Germany:</hi> Prince and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple?<note place="margin">Hiſt. Flor. lib. 1. Guiccard. lib. 1. Machi. hiſt. Flor. lib. 1.</note> Inſomuch as <hi>Machauell</hi> could note the Romaine Church to bee the cauſe of all the calamities of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taly.</hi> What ſhould I here relate the hurliburlies rayſed and increaſed by <hi>Iulius</hi> the ſecond? the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters cauſed by <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third,<note place="margin">Of Nice, and Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtantinopl. Synod. Carthag. can. 6.2 q. 2. c. placuit. c. 36. Gratian. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>renouintes. Tonſtal burned Engliſh teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at Paules croſſe.</note> and <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third? theſe may giue vs a taſt, that their whole reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is but politique <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> It were worth the noting to marke how they corrupt the ſcriptures: ſuppreſſe the trueth, depraue the auncient counſels: falſifie <hi>Synods,</hi> change the Canons, ſet vp fictions, diſplace antiquities; forge nouel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; falſifie laws; faine authors; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert tables; burne bills; ſet ſome of the fathers vpon the racke, &amp; thruſt the reſt into purgatory. Witnes one for many: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> their chiefe champion, whoſe pollicy is
<pb facs="tcp:14671:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſometime to change the ſtate of the cauſe at his pleaſure: ſometime to trouble the whole order with new diſtinctions on the wordes: Now to giue one and the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor yea one and the ſame booke both the liking and the lie,<note place="margin">Index expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorius.</note> as it ſhall be for him, or againſt him: then to turne the affirmatiue ſentences of the fathers into Negatiues,<note place="margin">Abraham. Sculteti. Epiſt. nucupator.</note> and their negatiues into affirmatiues: otherwhiles to quote halfe a ſpeach and period for the whole: and then againe to bring in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeites among the fathers coine: yea and to preferre the barbarous tranſlations of the Latins (if they ſerue his turne) before the purity of the <hi>Grecian</hi> coppies, that make not for him. And it is no pollicie to keepe their nouices fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reading the booke of proteſtants?<note place="margin">Concil. Trid.</note> or was it not foxlike cruelty to condemne <hi>William Tolwin</hi> for an heretick, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:14671:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>maiſter of artes, becauſe he had bookes of <hi>Frith,</hi> and <hi>Ridley, Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thon,</hi> and the confeſſion of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno. 1541.</note> compelling him to recant it at Paules croſſe?<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. de Rom. pontific. 2. &amp; 3.</note> And now men muſt build their faith vpon the Popes mouth, for he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not err. Yet <hi>Liberius</hi> was an <hi>Arrian: Acaſias</hi> 2 <hi>Nouatian: Honorius</hi> 2 <hi>Monothelite. Silueſter</hi> the 2. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 18.<note place="margin">Gratian. 2. diſt. 19. Platina. Luitprand.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the 19. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 20. <hi>Bennet</hi> the 8. <hi>Bennet</hi> the 9. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. were Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancers. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. maintained o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen ſtewes. <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d guilty of hereſie, murder,<note place="margin">Faſcie. tempo Theod. a Nieen lib 3. cap. 9. Abbas Vrſperg.</note> Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: and <hi>Iohn</hi> the 14. was conuicted of hereſie by the counſell of Conſtance. Howbeit the Papiſts would not beleeue the ſcriptures, no not <hi>Chriſtum natum, paſſum</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Benno Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> that Chrſt was borne, ſuffred, roſe, neither the reſurrection, life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the trinity, no nor that there was a God, <hi>Niſipropter eccleſiae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritatem,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>but for the authority of their Church: and yet the church depends vpon the Pope,<note place="margin">Stapleton lib. 1. 10. ſect. 3. &amp;c. 2 ſect. 6. &amp;c 2.13. ſect. 12.</note> 
               <hi>qui pleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in ſe fidei habet, quantum Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum imperator,</hi> who for the moſt part hath as much faith and religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in him,<note place="margin">Whittach. cont. Staplet. oc au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. ſact. ſcript. lib. 1. cap. 2.</note> as their great Turke. And I pray you what more high way can there be vnto Atheiſme, then to build faith ſcriptures, church, and all vpon the Pope, in whome is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a maſſe of hereſie, and infidelity? No maruell now, if the canon of the ſcripture be ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine among the Papiſts, ſeeing the Pope may detract, &amp; adde vnto it what he liſt. If the third councell of <hi>Carthage</hi> decree vpon a canon,<note place="margin">Trid. concil. ſeſſ. 4. cap. 2.</note> yet may the councell of <hi>Trident</hi> adde vnto it <hi>Baruch</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus:</hi> by the priuiledge of his Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>Rhenatus Bcnedictus</hi> vpon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion may adde the 3.<note place="margin">Lib. 1. cap. 8. ſtromar.</note> &amp; 4. books of <hi>Eſdras</hi> to the Canon. And his
<pb facs="tcp:14671:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>papacie may put in more into the canon, then either the Fathers,<note place="margin">Concil. Laod. c. 84. Origin. Gelaſius. Nazianz. Hieron in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. Galiato. Athanaſ. in ſynopſ. ſacr. ſcript.</note> or the <hi>Laodicean</hi> councell: and for the interpretations of the ſcriptures, if the Romiſts interpret it, it muſt ſtand for the word of God, be it meuer ſo falſe and ridiculous. But can the Papiſts deride their religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? How thinke you? what did <hi>Hildebrand</hi> the Pope whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he asked councell of the diuell?<note place="margin">Hoſius de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſ. verbo Dei.</note> or the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops &amp; the ſacrifiſing Prieſts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Satans iudgement &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie touching the ruine of the <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentines, ſigno dato hoſtiam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benno Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> 
               <hi>id eſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ſuum igni inijciunt:</hi> when they receiued a diſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented ſigne,<note place="margin">Volater. lib. 5. Georg.</note> they threw their hoſt, that is their God into the fire. <hi>Boniface</hi> the 8. becauſe <hi>Procherus</hi> tooke part with the <hi>Gibel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Harding. Confut. Apol. Anglic.</note> which were his aduerſaries, ſaid vnto him vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aſhwedneſday the ſolemne day of aſhes: <hi>memento homo quod Gibellinus es,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concil. Later ſeſſ. 10. ſub. Leone. 10.</note> 
               <hi>et cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gibelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in terra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reuerteris.</hi> Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>(not that thou art aſhes) but that thou art of the ſtocke, and facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Gibellines,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nauclerus Ann. 677 Agathon in the firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell at Conſtantinople.</note> and that with the <hi>Gibellines</hi> thou ſhalt returne vnto the earth, and forthwith he threw aſhes in his face. Do they not defend whoredome, taking tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute <hi>à meretricibus</hi> of ſtewes and harlots? do they not defend vſury, and call them <hi>montes pietatis</hi> rockes and mountaines of piety and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion? And was not <hi>Iohannes de Caſa</hi> an arche Prelate, that wrote a Booke in the commendation of Sodomy?<note place="margin">Sinon caſte tamen caute.</note> To omit their baptizing of Bels, and their other fopperies: are not theſe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to ſhew, what houſe they come of?<note place="margin">Agrippa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>duerſ. Louani<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nſ.</note> did not <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius</hi> call marriage beaſtlineſſe, and yet himſelfe had three baſtards, the ſame yeare he diſputed thereof at <hi>Lipſia?</hi> But theſe chaſte patrons do not forſweare fornication, adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and vncleaneneſſe, but onely
<pb facs="tcp:14671:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>lawful wedlocke, and honeſt mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.<note place="margin">Roſſ. lib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt. reip Chriſt. Imp. eap 5.</note> If I ſhould tell you what ſmal conſcience theſe Papiſts make of rayling, ſlaundering,<note place="margin">Hard. in defenſ. Apol.</note> lying &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming, their <hi>Atheiſme</hi> would be ouer plaine and palpable. Who ſo ſhall read <hi>Alanus: Briſtow: Staple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: Riſhton: Hamilton,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. praefat. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> controu. de Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Bozius, Vlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge, Verſtergan, Ecchius, Cocleus: Stapilus: Bolſecus: Bellarmine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſt. vbiq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and the Rhemiſh teſtament: where they call the proteſtants, <hi>Turkes, Pagans,</hi> Monſters, miracles, <hi>Gerions, Briareans, Minotaurs, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taures,</hi> lyers, impudent, fooliſh, ſhameles, ignorant, witles, iewiſh,<note place="margin">Staple. in Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tak. &amp; de Iewello <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. 9.</note> heatheniſh, blaſphemous, villaines, harlots, madmen, theues, coblers, cananites, apoſtates, heretickes, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells, letchers, tinkers, tapſters, fid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, pipers, that they make no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the articles of their faith,<note place="margin">Bellar. denotis Eccleſ. lib. 4. cap. 8.</note> and ſuch like, may eaſily diſcerne in them the ſpirit of the dragon and of <hi>Atheiſme.</hi> They make no bones
<pb facs="tcp:14671:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>to bely religious and good men (ſo they might colour their religion) as you may ſee by theſe two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in ſteede of many.</p>
            <p>They write that <hi>Caluin</hi> calling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the diuel, blaſpheming &amp; ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring gaue vp the ghoſt, curſing the day when he began to apply him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to ſtudy and writing: yea that in his life time he had forſaken the Church of God,<note place="margin">Cyprian.</note> and betaken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to papiſme: but <hi>mendacia di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> non fallunt:</hi> lyes laſt not long: For <hi>Caluin</hi> anſwering for himſelfe ſaith: <hi>fallitur Diabolus cum tota ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> caterua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calu. in Epiſt. inſtit. Chriſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>ſi me putidis ſuis mendacijs obruendo, hacindignitate fractiorem ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> magis lentum fore putat: quia De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um proſua immenſa bonitate daturum mthico<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſido, vt in curſu ſanctae ſuae vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cationis aequabili tolerantia perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem:</hi> the diuell is deceiued with all his army, if ouercharging me with their ſtinking lies he thinks by this indignitie to weaken and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb facs="tcp:14671:42" rendition="simple:additions"/>me: becauſe I truſt that God of his goodnes will ſo inable me as I ſhall perſeuere in the courſe of his holy calling, with the ſame paines, and patience. And of <hi>Beza</hi> they ſet out many copies in print, that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe at his death did turne Papiſt &amp; with him the whole church of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neua</hi> in this ſort.<note place="margin">Theod Reza. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oan Gui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Stuck<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Sac. The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>log. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Tiguri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. profeſſ. Epiſt. &amp; paſtorum ac profeſſ. Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſ reſponſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on put<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diſſ. &amp; impudentiſſ. Commentum Monachorum ſacr. nomen Ieſu ementium de The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dori Bez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> obi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dem ac totius Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Genauen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionem.</note> 
               <hi>Theodorus Beza vt ſemortivicinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenſit, cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleno ſenatu Geneuenſi palinodiam cecinit, hortans et per dei amore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſenatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> totum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uenſem rogans, vt ſi cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redes Chriſti in aeterna vita eſſe velint relicto errore Caluiniſmi, ad catholicae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dis obſeruanti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m et religionem toto pectore ſeſe conuerterent, &amp;c.</hi> which <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe ſuruiuing conuicted of falſhood, &amp; the whole Church of <hi>Geneua</hi> writing in their owne &amp; his behalfe proued to be a deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſlander &amp; ſham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les lying fictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And are they leſſe liberall of their blaſphemies that ſay we are able to do more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ought, yea <hi>pluſqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14671:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>reuer a facere teneamur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 2. de Monach. cap. 13</note> more then we are bound to doe by the law of God. And if we cannot keepe the law of God <hi>Deus eſſet omni tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ini quior et crudelior:</hi> then were God more cruell and vniuſt then any tyrant.<note place="margin">Naziacez.</note> Notwithſtanding <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: not to ſinne is aboue the reach of man.<note place="margin">Rhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. Tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Aquin. ſupple. 25. q. art. 1.</note> And what Papiſt ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue the Lord with all his hart, minde, ſoule, and ſtrength, that make the Pope equal to God and his Chriſt? <hi>Papa et Chriſtus faciunt vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conſiſtorium</hi> the Pope and Chriſt make one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory. That ſay <hi>Francis</hi> did as much as Chriſt <hi>imo plura fecit quam Chriſtus:</hi> yea he did more then Chriſt.<note place="margin">Pomormitan. lib. confirmitat.</note> That call the ſcriptures dumbe,<note place="margin">Defenſ. Apol. Iewell.</note> dead, and Inckhorne diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, yea &amp; deny there is any iot of diuinity in them, <hi>que nos ad crede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum:</hi> that can bind vs by religion to beleeue them.<note place="margin">Pigh. 3. de eccl. Eckius.</note> Is not this the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry top of <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> to deny the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſcriptures to be the word of God?<note place="margin">Andrad. lib. 3. defenſ. concil. Trid.</note> For this cauſe they haue printed bookes of the inſufficiency of the ſcriptures, &amp; the vncertainty of the ſame.<note place="margin">Ecchius. Enchir. de author. eccle. reſp. 3. de ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. haeret.</note> And now they muſt not bee Authenticke <hi>niſi eccleſiae authoritate</hi> vnleſſe the Church authorize the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For <hi>omnis quae nunc eſt ſcriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum authoritas, ab eccleſiae authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te dependet neceſſario:</hi> all the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which now the ſcripture hath, depends neceſſarily vpon the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the church.<note place="margin">Pighſus lib. 1. de H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rarch. Eccleſ. cap. 2.</note> No neither ſhould they be cannonicall, nor be of any force among the Papiſts <hi>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi nos eccleſiae doceret authoritas:</hi> but for the authority of their Church: yea <hi>tantum valent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſſius. lib. 3. de author. ſcrip.</note> 
               <hi>quantum Aeſopi fabulae:</hi> but for the teſtimony of their Church, they would eſteeme no more of the ſcriptures, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they doe of <hi>Aeſops</hi> fables.<note place="margin">Hoſſius. lib. 2. cont. Bren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> No maruell then if they make <hi>Dauid</hi> a Ballad maker, and equall fables, Canons, Epiſtles, Extrauagants, Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>and traditions with the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or if they make new ſcriptures as <hi>Nouum Euangelium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſius lib. de verbo Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the new goſpell,<note place="margin">Andrad lib. 2. Lindan lib. 1. c. 4. &amp; 5. diſt. 15. Sancta Roma.</note> our Ladies Pſalter, the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gends of Martirs: new ſacraments, prefer traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aboue the ſcripture and make traditions the foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſcriptures. <hi>Scripturae au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas euaneſcit penitus, niſieam tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio in ſundamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtabiliat,</hi> wheras no <hi>Turke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. Cuſpian de Saracenis.</note> or <hi>Sarace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> dare change one iot of <hi>Mahomets</hi> lawe: the Papiſts dare change the law of God: take the cup fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people, decreed by Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 23,<note place="margin">Baptiſta. Pane. c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us.</note> in the counſel of <hi>Conſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce:</hi> mingle water with wine, &amp; ad ſalt, ſpittle, oyle, exorciſmes, &amp; what not vnto baptiſme. Yet the ſcripture permits none to know a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue that which is written,<note place="margin">Bellar. lib. 1. de baptiſm. c. 2. &amp; 27. 1. Corinth. 4. 1. Galathians. 3. Romans.</note> no not an Angel from heauen: for euery man is a lyer, but God is true. And ſo is the Pope (ſaith the Papiſt) for he is a God. What now remaines, if God ſent vs the ſcriptures for a
<pb facs="tcp:14671:44" rendition="simple:additions"/>rule for our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but to bel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eue they be both true &amp; ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for vs, or elſe to imagine that God in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either could not, wold not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> durſt not reueale the truth vnto vs, which is groſe Atheiſme once to ſuppoſe. Indeed the old hereticks indeuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to deface woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne wedlock,<note place="margin">Clemens. Alex. lib. 3. ſtrom.</note> alledged teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>ex quoda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euangelio Apocripho ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Aegiptios:</hi> out of a certaine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriphal goſpel, according to the <hi>Aegiptians:</hi> &amp; from the goſpel of S. <hi>Iames.</hi> The <hi>Manickes</hi> held the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to be corrupt: <hi>Heluidius</hi> was perſwaded that the <hi>Greeke</hi> copies were falſe,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. 1. de mor. cap. 29.</note> yea the heretickes, not daring to ſtand to the Canonicall ſcriptures, vſed <hi>Apocrypha</hi> as the goſpell of the <hi>Hebrewes:</hi> the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of <hi>Euah:</hi> the goſpell of <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> the goſpell of <hi>Nicodemus;</hi> the goſpell of perfection: the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our Ladye the more and the leſſe: the reuelation of <hi>Adam</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſo forth: many of theſe had the diſciples of <hi>Marrion:</hi> And <hi>Tatian</hi> from the foure Euangeliſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded a diateſſeron as a ouiteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for his followers.<note place="margin">Concil. Trid. ſeſſ. 4. decr. 2. Bellar. lib. 2. deſcript. cap. 2. &amp; de verbo De lib. 2. cap. 10.</note> The Papiſts not behind with any, hold the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew text to be corrupt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a athorize only the latin: how be it <hi>Iſodorus Clarius</hi> ſaith: that in the latin,<note place="margin">Iſid. Epiſt. ad lector ante ver fione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> biblioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and common interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion there be inumerable faultes, whereof he amended 8 thouſand in his tranſlation: notwithſtanding for all his paines, his tranſlatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was condemned by the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. For Apocrypha they haue <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teuangelium Iacobi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Goſpell of <hi>Iames,</hi> the lyturgy of <hi>Iames:</hi> the Goſpell of <hi>Nicodemus Prochorus</hi> his hiſtory of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Euangeliſt: the Epiſtles of <hi>Martialis: Abdias</hi> of the liues of the Apoſtles, and (to omit all the reſt) <hi>nouum euangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cyrilli cuiuſdam monachi Carmelitae</hi> a new goſpel of a certaine <hi>Camelite</hi> Monk
<pb facs="tcp:14671:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>named <hi>Cyrillus,</hi> the ſum whereof is <hi>deum patrem ſub lege, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. de Poe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ir. cap. 8. Math.</note> God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ather raigned in the time of the law: God the ſonne in the time of grace, but now the 4. begging or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders being erected, the holy Ghoſt is authorized in his kingdome,<note place="margin">Pariſienſ. Thom. Cranti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prat.</note> and ſhall ſo continue to the end of the world, &amp; who ſo wil be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ued, muſt of neceſſity beleeue this goſpell &amp; yet many withſtood as <hi>Gulielme de ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cto amore: Guid. Bonatus</hi> who writ a booke againſt it: But <hi>Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fred</hi> king of <hi>Cicily</hi> was excommunicated by the Pope,<note place="margin">Faſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. tempor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Ioh. Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. tom. 2.</note> becauſe he deteſted this goſpell: <hi>Gerardus Saragellus</hi> was burned at <hi>Parma</hi> for refuſing it. Thus they diſable the word of God to ſet vp their owne inuentions: which how it may be without <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme</hi> I reſt to be inſtructed by the pollitick Papiſt.<note place="margin">Greg. Epiſt. 3. lib. 11. Seculius 2. Tueſſal. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Gregory</hi> and <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulius</hi> pointing out vnto vs Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, affirme <hi>Antichriſtum Iudacias ceremonias reuocaturu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> that antichriſt
<pb facs="tcp:14671:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhould call againe the Iewiſh cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies. But the Papiſts haue reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the church both with Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſme and Gentiliſme,<note place="margin">Euſcb. lib. 5. cap. 14.15.19. &amp;c.</note> yet <hi>Blaſtus</hi> was counted an heretick, <hi>quod late<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vult Iudaiſmum introducere:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he laboured vnder-hand to bring <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> into the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. lib. de praeſcript. haeret.</note> And ſaith <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Aquin, Gentilitatis ritus repudiabatur tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnino illicitus, et a Deo ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>per prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus. Ritus aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> legis ceſſabat tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> impletus per Chriſti paſsionem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aqui. 1.2. Q. 103. Art. 4.</note> 
               <hi>vtpote a Deo in figur am Chriſti conſtitutus:</hi> the rites &amp; ceremonies of the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> were reiected &amp; refuſed, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vnlawfull,<note place="margin">Boemus. Aubanus de gent. mor.</note> &amp; for euer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: but the ceremonies of the law did ceaſe, as being fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the paſſion of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Guicciard. funerall 1. Blondus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ium. Mantuan. faſt. Belethus. Aug. de confeſſ. Euang. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> being ordained of God to be a figure of Chriſt. Notwithſtanding the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts haue borrowed of both, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping God after another man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner then he had preſcribed: &amp; not ſeruing Chriſt according to the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:46" rendition="simple:additions"/>knowledge of the truth.<note place="margin">Lactan. lib. 5. cap.10. 1. Sam. 5. 22. Numb. 1. King. 11. 1. King. 13. 2. King. 5. 5. Iohn. 23.15. Math. 9.</note> The <hi>Aegip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> ſerued God vnder the ſhapes of beaſts: the <hi>Philiſtins</hi> vnder the ſhape of <hi>Dagon</hi> a Fiſh; the <hi>Graecians</hi> of a man; the <hi>Caldeans</hi> had their <hi>Baal;</hi> the <hi>Sidonians</hi> had their <hi>Aſhte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roth; Amonites, Moloch; Syrians, Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non,</hi> and ſo forth: yea thus did the <hi>Iewes, Arrians, Mahometiſts</hi> worſhip God otherwiſe then he had reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his word. For they honored not the Sonne, as they did the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but ſerued him,<note place="margin">Lactan. de fall. relig. lib. 2. c. 20</note> teaching for doctrines the commandements of men. Yet the Papiſt ſerues &amp; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents God in an Idoll, and many wayes like the Iewes &amp; Heathens doth diſhonor him.<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa. 113. 1. Romanes. Pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>haed. Virgil. Aeneid. 1</note> For the <hi>Gentile</hi> could ſay, <hi>no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ipſa timemus, ſed eos ad quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> imagine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ficta, et quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nomini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus conſecrata ſunt:</hi> we neither feare nor worſhip the Image,<note place="margin">Plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>arch. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra viudict.</note> but the thing repreſented by the Image: And yet <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſaith, that the <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile</hi> turned the trueth of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a lye: namely the glorie of the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>incorruptible God, into the ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of a corruptible man.<note place="margin">Boemus de Gent. mor. lib. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.5.</note> The Heathens praied to the dead, as <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> to <hi>Anchiſes:</hi> ſo do the Papiſts. The heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s made a Purgatory ſo do the Papiſts.<note place="margin">Bellar. de cleria. lib. 1. cap. 19. diſt. 82.</note> The Heathens had ſhauen crownes, turnings in the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, ſacrifiſings, pompous ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, adorations, muſicall mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,<note place="margin">Pol. Virg. lib. 5. cap. 4.</note> &amp;c. and ſo haue the Papiſts: their Prieſts muſt be ſingle becauſe the legall Prieſts did ſeperate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from their wiues in their courſe of ſacrifice: wherefore <hi>Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius</hi> will forbid Prieſts marriages: and <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. wil take it cleane away.<note place="margin">Clemens. Alex. lib. 3. ſtrom.</note> Howbeit (ſaith <hi>Clemens</hi>) the hereticks tooke occaſion to forbid prieſts mariages <hi>ex Ethnicorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplis,</hi> from the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. Thus they tooke examples <hi>ab Hieraophntis Athenienſibus</hi> from the <hi>Athenian</hi> expounders,<note place="margin">Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>on. lib. 2. cont. Iouiman.</note> who loſt their ſtrength with drinking Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock: &amp; vnder pretence of puritie,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:47" rendition="simple:additions"/>excluded lawfull wedlocke from their idolatrous ſacrifices, ſaying:
<q>
                  <l>abſiſtat à ſacris<note place="margin">Euſch. de praep.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Cui tulis heſterna gaudia nocte Venus.<note place="margin">Euang. 18.</note>
                  </l>
               </q>Of this hereſie were ſometime the <hi>Eſſens,</hi> borrowing their kinde of life from <hi>Pythagoras</hi> rules, the firſt chapter whereof was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Adamites.</note> the contemot of marriage. Some thinke their prohibitions came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the goſpell of <hi>S. Iames,</hi> others from the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Guido per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. de Haereſib.</note> that knew not his wife before his fall: other from <hi>Abdias</hi> the <hi>Babylonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> writing of the Acts of the Apoſtles: but howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Mantua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> ſets this brand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Romulidu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leges quaeſunt conubia contra.</l>
               <l>Eſſe malas vere prohibent, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>That thoſe <hi>Romiſh</hi> lawes are full of impiety and vngodlineſſe.<note place="margin">Belſar. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nach. lib. 1. c. 5.</note> If the <hi>Nazurites</hi> and <hi>Rechabites</hi> had their vowes, the Papiſts will runne in debt vnto them for their Monkes, &amp; votaries: If <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> faſt fortie dayes,<note place="margin">Rhem. in Math. 4. ſect. 2.</note> they muſt needes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foord the Papiſts the time of Lent
<pb facs="tcp:14671:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>from their examples: <hi>Paule</hi> the firſt will lend vnto it a lenten ſeruice: and <hi>Gregory</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Popiſh libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity will ad 4. dayes vnto it: yet he will take away Milke,<note place="margin">Polyd. Virg. lib. 6. cap. 6. 5. Numb. 19. Numb.</note> Cheeſe, But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Egges; And if the papiſts haue neede of conſecrated oyle,<note place="margin">Bellar. de cultu. ſanct. 3. lib. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſalt, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, aſhes, they muſt come a beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to the Iewes.<note place="margin">Sigebert. Volater. Polyd. lib. 5. cap. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Innocentius,</hi> and <hi>Foelix</hi> the fourth will beſtowe it kindely vpon the ſick. But <hi>Silueſter</hi> will haue the Biſhops anoynted after the manner of the <hi>Leuiticall</hi> Prieſts.<note place="margin">Bellar. de ſacra. confir. lib. 2. c. 8.</note> And if the lawe preſcribe anoyntings, the Papiſts wil be bold to borrow it.<note place="margin">Leuit. 4.</note> &amp; <hi>Damaſus</hi> will haue the croſſing with <hi>Chriſme</hi> vpon the brow at baptiſme: yea if the Iewes had their ſacrifices for ſinne, the Popes will haue their Maſſe,<note place="margin">Bellar. de miſſa lib. 2. cap. 2. Platina. lib. 8. &amp; 9.</note> or els they will runne vpon the ſcore: yea here the Pope will ſhew his libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: <hi>Gregory</hi> will giue vnto it the <hi>Antiphonae</hi> and 9. times <hi>Kyrieleiſon.</hi> Yea if needes be, whatſoeuer <hi>Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Sixtus, Innocentius</hi> the firſt, <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:14671:48" rendition="simple:additions"/>the firſt, <hi>Gelaſius, Leo</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue begunne, he will alter, and change, ſaying: <hi>ſancti Patres no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtatim omnia ad decorum officij per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinentia videre potuerunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Lornbard, de tribus varie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tatibus miſſa.</note> 
               <hi>ſed diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi diuerſa ordinauerunt:</hi> the holy fathers could not ſee all that was needefull for ſo high a ſeruice as the Maſſe, whence grew a contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie, whether the <hi>Ambroſian,</hi> or the <hi>Gregorian</hi> ſeruice were to be preferred. But downe went the <hi>Ambroſian</hi> in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, with fire and faggot both for it, and the vpholders thereof. And the firſt Lattin Maſſe was ſung at the ſixt <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> in the yeare 656. the true nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of antichriſt.<note place="margin">Sanguine miſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uit. Bale in Centuar. cap. 8 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Sergius</hi> beſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon it <hi>agnus dei</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> others the worſhiping of the hoſt at <hi>Eleuatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> as alſo the carriage of it with lightes and other ſuperſtitions vnto the ſick others borrowed maſſing gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the attrying of the prieſts
<pb facs="tcp:14671:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the old law: <hi>Stephanus</hi> ordained altars after the maner of the Iewes: <hi>Silueſter</hi> beſtowed both linne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Albes</hi> and corporals,<note place="margin">Rellar. de Miſſa lib. 2. cap. 15. Poly. lib. 6. c. 12 Platina.</note> yet <hi>Sixtus</hi> will not haue the Prieſt to weare his robes but in an holy place. If <hi>Salomons</hi> Temple be all gorgious, they will adorne their Churches, with ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">Bellar. de miſſa. lib. 2 cap. 6. Polyd. li. 6. c. 13.</note> Croſſes, Golde &amp;c, becauſe of his example. If <hi>Conſtantine</hi> in the yeare 707. giue leaue for Images to be painted in S. <hi>Peters</hi> porch at <hi>Rome: Gregory</hi> the third in the yeare 731. will haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be worſhiped.<note place="margin">Lenit. 13.</note> And becauſe the Leuiticall Prieſts had the diſcerning of the leprous perſons: the Popiſh Prieſts muſt haue auricular confeſſion,<note place="margin">Bellar. de paeni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 3. c. 3.</note> yea it muſt be a ſacrament, <hi>et ſine hac non patere viam ad caelum</hi> and without this,<note place="margin">Lombard lib. 4 diſt. 17.</note> there muſt be no way where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to enter into heauen: yet <hi>Gratia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> doubted of it: <hi>Auguſtine</hi> wrought againſt it: &amp; in the church <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Innocent. 3. in com. lat. c. 21.</note> defending the vnity of eſſence, it
<pb facs="tcp:14671:49" rendition="simple:additions"/>was altogether abrogated.<note place="margin">Gratian. diſt 1. de paenit.</note> But leaſt the Papiſt ſhould be leſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> either Iew or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile: <hi>Leo</hi> the third appointed the burning of Frankincenſe,<note place="margin">Aug. confeſſ. 10 cap. 3.</note> after the manner both of Iewes and Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles: <hi>Silueſter</hi> ordained the feaſt of <hi>Petri ad Vincula;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hiſt. Tripart. lib. 9. cap. 35. Polyd. li. 5. c. 10 Poly. lib. 6. c. 8. Sigebert volat. Extrau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan.</note> 
               <hi>Vigilius</hi> the feaſt of Candlemas: <hi>Honorius</hi> the feaſt of the exaltation of the croſſe: <hi>Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banus</hi> the 4. Corpus Chriſti day. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth the dayes of the preſentation,<note place="margin">Poly. de In. lib. 6. cap. 8. Platina. Sabell.</note> and conception of our Lady, of Saint <hi>Anne,</hi> and of <hi>Ioſeph. Iohn</hi> the eighteenth the feaſt of all ſoules. And <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the 4. the feaſt of all Saints, <hi>Boniface</hi> beſtowed vpon the Saints faſting euens.<note place="margin">Polydor. 6. c. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Sergius</hi> ſhrines. <hi>Gregory</hi> veneration. <hi>Leo</hi> hymnes,<note place="margin">Iacob. Bergo. menſ.</note> 
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. a ſaints bell to be tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thriſe euery day,<note place="margin">Platina. Naucler.</note> whereat the hearers ſhould ſtreight wayes crowch downe and ſay the <hi>Auae
<pb facs="tcp:14671:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>Maria.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Polyd. 6. ca. 12. Platina. Polyd. li. 6. c. 11 Gratian. Iſidor. Volat. Platina. Sauel. Sigebret. Polyd. lib. 6. cap. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Foelix</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated altars, and <hi>Boniface</hi> beſtowed both church &amp; altars on theeues for ſanctuaries. <hi>Innocentius</hi> muſt haue the Pax car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried about on feſtiuall dayes to be kiſſed: <hi>Vrbanus</hi> the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion cup to be of gold. <hi>Zozimus</hi> the Paſcall taper on Eaſter eeuen to be hallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Vitellian</hi> organs, and inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts in the church. <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Pſalmes to be ſung after the order of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phones. Leo</hi> Maſſe for the dead. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius</hi> &amp; <hi>Vrbanus</hi> canonical houres. <hi>Gregory</hi> large proceſſions: <hi>Leo</hi> pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie proceſſions;<note place="margin">Greg. 4. Epiſt. cap. 88.</note> and <hi>Agapetus</hi> muſt haue thoſe proceſſions to go round about the church euery Sunday.<note place="margin">Polyd. li. 6. c. 11. Greg. 4. Epiſt. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. Polyd. 6. cap. 11. Volat. Platina. Martin. Carſu. Ian. Hugo. Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria cenſ. Ptolom Luce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. Godfrid.</note> Behold how they worſhip God af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne fantacies, putting therevnto canonicall houres, Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tins, Maſſe, Proceſſion, Senſing, Saints, holydayes, compleine, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanies, Inuocations, Images, Dir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for the dead, Ladies Pſalters,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:50" rendition="simple:additions"/>Baptized Bels, Beads, Altars,<note place="margin">Viterbius. Anronius Plor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t Iohn Ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us. Guliel. Durand. in rat. diuino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans, Songs, Wax, lights, Banners, reliques, croſſes, holy water, and forraine toungs. Yea oyle, creame, ſpittle, vnctions, ſhauings, aſhes, watchings, pageants, vowes, pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimages, faſtings, and a world of fenceleſſe ceremonies. Is not this to change the worſhip of God into idolatry, ſuperſtition, humaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uentions, mens commandements, and vtterly to aboliſh it? <hi>Bethen e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim quae prius vocabatur domus Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron in Oſea lib. 1. cap. 4.</note>
               <hi>poſtquam vittuli in ea poſiti ſunt, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thauen er at, id eſt domus inutilis, et domus Idoli:</hi> For <hi>Bethel</hi> that before was called the houſe of God, after the Calues were placed in it, was <hi>Bethauen</hi> the houſe of Idols; then what can the church of <hi>Rome</hi> be, but <hi>Bethauen,</hi> that ſets vp the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Angels; Inuocation of the dead, adoration of the croſſe, of Images, of reliques, of the bread in the ſacrament, with all
<pb facs="tcp:14671:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe ſuperſtitious ceremonies,<note place="margin">Guliel. Whita. aduerſ. Staplet. praefat. ad lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> &amp; many more before recounted. But let the whole religion of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry be a profeſſion of a coloured <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> a good life wil mend all: <hi>modo habeant bonos motus rationi na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ali conuenientes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Scotus prolog. ſent. q. 12.</note> 
               <hi>caueantque eaquae ratio natur alis mala et fugienda eſſe docet:</hi> If they neither be baptiſed, not haue any Church, or teaching, yet they may be ſaued, if they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a good minde, haue an honeſt intent, and walke according to the lawes of nature, and reaſon, as the Papiſts do. For they,<note place="margin">Barnard de. conſid. ad Euge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. lib. 4. Barnard. in ſerm. 33.</note> 
               <hi>ante omnia ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientes ſunt vt faciant mala, bonum autem facere neſciunt, blandiſsimi a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimpliciſsimi diſsimulatores, et malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulatores, mordaciſsimi detractores, niſsimi proditores:</hi> are wiſe to do e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil, but know not how to do good, moſt fawning flatterers, biting ſla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,<note place="margin">Holcot. in Sap. Lect. 183.</note> deepe diſſemblers, &amp; mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious traitors: Prieſts of <hi>Baal, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:51" rendition="simple:additions"/>Priapus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. praefat. Didym. de ſpiri. tu ſancto. Bernard. in cant. 33. &amp; in conuer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſancti Paul. ſerm. 1.</note> Angels of hell. <hi>Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus phariſaeorum, Coloni purpuratae meretricis: Babylonians,</hi> Phariſes, inhabitants of the purple colou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red whore, ſeruantes of Antichriſt: perſecutors of Chriſt and his Church: ſicke from the ſoale of the foote, to the crowne of the head: roaring Lyons, and deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Wolues. Many goe vnto <hi>Rome</hi> ſome what good, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne very bad. <hi>Eugenius aſcendit Iericho, incidit in latrones: Eugenius</hi> was fetcht to <hi>Rome</hi> to be Pope,<note place="margin">Hieron. in Soph. 5.</note> he went vp to <hi>Iericho,</hi> but he fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theeues.<note place="margin">Grego. hom. 17 in Ezechi. Hieron. in Ier. 2.</note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Proh pudor hos toler are poteſt eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia porcos,</l>
               <l>Duntaxat ventri, veneri, ſomnoque vacantes:</l>
            </q>
            <p>O ſhame, can any Church ſtil ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Papiſtry,<note place="margin">Bernard. Epiſt. 147.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That nought regardes but belly, ſleepe and venery?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>When <hi>Nertarius</hi> began to ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broach auricular confeſſion at <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Palinge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. lib. 9. in Sagittario.</note> a certaine Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being confeſſed of a Prieſt, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned to faſt,<note place="margin">Zoz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n. hiſt. trip. lib. 9.c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.35</note> pray in the Church, was in the time of her penance ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhed by an holy <hi>Deacon,</hi> which tooke great paines in the ſanctuary to obſerue the vow of chaſtity: wherupo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the peoples exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions it was there again diſſolued.<note place="margin">Cyprian. Epiſt. 11.</note> Pope <hi>Iohn</hi> the 13. was begotten by <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12. of an arrant ſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet;<note place="margin">Luitprand. lib. 2 cap. 13.</note> &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> the 10. was borne of fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Pope <hi>Sergius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohan. Textot. Henricus Agrip.</note> vpon an whore called <hi>Marozia:</hi> yea <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Lombard</hi> Maiſter of ſentences: <hi>Peter Comeſter</hi> Maiſter of hiſtories &amp; the Monke <hi>Gratian</hi> compiler o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the lawes,<note place="margin">Volate.</note> were borne betwixt an holy <hi>Nun</hi> &amp; a Prieſt.<note place="margin">Iohan Textor in offic.</note> 
               <hi>Philip</hi> the holy Abbot of <hi>Valliſolet,</hi> and archbiſhop of <hi>Hiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alis</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> kept <hi>Chriſtian</hi> his brother <hi>Alphonſus</hi> wife himſelf: ſtill liuing. <hi>Petrus Mendoſa</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb facs="tcp:14671:52" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Valens</hi> had two baſtards by <hi>Elizabeth</hi> wife to <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Boccace. Pogghius.</note> Some one ghoſtly father hath corrupted in his time a 100. Nunnes &amp; Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens: ſome 200. ſome more, ſome leſſe. <hi>Agrippa</hi> reporteth of a Biſhop,<note place="margin">Agrip. de incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titud. ſcient. cap. 64.</note> that boaſted at his table, that he had in his dioceſſe eleauen thouſand prieſts, which paind yearely a <hi>French</hi> crowne for whores keeping, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides occupying with other mens wiues. <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> that withſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the marriage of Prieſts, was himſelfe a <hi>Necromancer,</hi> a murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, a ſuppreſſer of princes, &amp; kept <hi>Maude</hi> the Duches of <hi>Lothary</hi> both in the daies of her huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Gozilon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lambard Shaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fan. in Cronicis</note>&amp; alſo after his death, leading her about with him in his Coach.<note place="margin">Ranulph in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycron. lib. 7. cap. 13.</note> At what time <hi>Iohannes de Cremona</hi> the Popes Legate <hi>à latere</hi> came from <hi>Rome</hi> vnto England to forbidde prieſts wiues,<note place="margin">Guliel. Maul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mesbuty. Flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. hiſt.</note> he was taken himſelfe with a whore the night following.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benno Cardinalis</hi> ſaith, that the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>finiſhing of the thouſand yeares,<note place="margin">Henry Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tington. lib. 7. Benno Card. in vita Hildebrand.</note> when the Dragon ſhould be loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, was in <hi>Pontificatu Sergij ſecundi</hi> in the Popedome of <hi>Sergius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, whom a diuell ſtrangled vpon a compact betweene him, and the Pope, as he was ſaying Maſſe in the open ſight of all men.<note place="margin">Au<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntinc. pag. 584.</note> Neither was it without cauſe, that the <hi>Germans</hi> called <hi>Hildebrand Hellebr and</hi> a fire brand of hell. But why do I inſiſt in theſe petty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?<note place="margin">Agripp. de Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocin. &amp; crat. ad Louanienſ.</note> did not Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> builde a ſtewes at <hi>Rome,</hi> which bring in yearely twenty thouſand Duck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates? yea what ſhould <hi>Boniface</hi> the 7. <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the 2. <hi>Bennet</hi> the 9. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 7. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 9. <hi>Innocenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the eight?<note place="margin">Luitprand. li. 6. cap. 6. and. 7.</note> did not <hi>Sixtus</hi> the fourth make a ſtewes at <hi>Rome,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing it both for Maſculine and Faeminine: &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> the twelfe made a ſtewes of his pallace,<note place="margin">Platina in vita Marcel.</note> and dranke a carouſe to the diuell. He
<pb facs="tcp:14671:53" rendition="simple:additions"/>that will know more let him ſearch <hi>Platina, Mantuan</hi> and others,<note place="margin">Mantuan Eclog. 5. Faſtor. 2. Sil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.</note> and he ſhall finde enough to make his eares to tingle. <hi>Budaeus</hi> ſpeaking of the French Biſhops ſaith,<note place="margin">Budaeus Annot. prior. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. de leg. pag. 121.</note> they were more like hogs then men <hi>prae morum turpitudine et inſcitia: Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch</hi> calleth the church of <hi>Rome ſcholam errorum:</hi> the temple of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, deflecting from the worſhip of God,<note place="margin">Petrach. cant. 106.107.108.</note> vnto the worſhip of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> and <hi>Venus:</hi> yea he calleth it <hi>Babylonia,</hi> and impudent harlot where <hi>verit as</hi> is <hi>dementia, abſtinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ruſticitas, pudicitia probru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hoſtis, malorum hoſpes:</hi> truth is madenes, abſtinence clownery, ſhamefaſtnes diſhoneſty, it is an hoſt for the wicked, an enemy to the godly. And from thence comes all the miſchiefe in the world.<note place="margin">Vinon. Labyt. tract. 5. cap. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Theodorus</hi> a <hi>Niem</hi> recording the <hi>Schiſme</hi> betweene <hi>Vrban</hi> the 6. and <hi>Clement,</hi> relates of nothing but
<pb facs="tcp:14671:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>warres, ſeditions, murders, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, luſtes and ambitions: and ſpeaking of the Nunnes &amp; Monkes from the teſtimony fo <hi>Gregory</hi> the 12. he calleth them <hi>ebrios, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubinarios, homicidas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gualter Mape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fius in Rhyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius.</note> drunkardes, letchers, murderers, with many other tearmes befitting rather di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uells then men. Some call their prelates <hi>Haeredes Luciferi,</hi> heires of Lucifer: others ſay their monaſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries <hi>praeter Penelopes ſponſos, Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lones,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stiblinus in Cornupedia.</note>
               <hi>Alcinooſque neminem h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>die e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducunt:</hi> nouriſh none but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons,<note place="margin">Briden brach. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uae peregr. hiſtor.</note> knaues, whores, &amp; ribbaldes. Some compare their officers to Pilates ſleeping on the ſea: to dogs that cannot barke, to watchmen without their trumpets. <hi>O tempor a, O mores: Gaude mater Roma et quia per malitiam hominum, non per tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am religionem orbem viciſti:</hi> reioyce Ô <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abbas Vrſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſ. de Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſ. 3. &amp; Boni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fac. 8.</note> becauſe thou haſt van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed the world, not by thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
<pb facs="tcp:14671:54" rendition="simple:additions"/>but by the wickedneſſe of thy people.<note place="margin">Brigit Anno. 1370.</note> Thy Prieſts haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Gods ten commaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ements into one precept, <hi>dap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cuniam</hi> giue,<note place="margin">Onuphrlus.</note> giue, <hi>Paulus</hi> the 4. ſet vp vſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry: <hi>luli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the 3. was an extortioner, and <hi>Pius</hi> the 4. prayed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the church,<note place="margin">Faſcic. tempot Luitprand. Flatina.</note> 
               <hi>Vigilius, Iohn</hi> the 11. <hi>Conſtantius</hi> the 2. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12. <hi>Benedict</hi> the 5. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 19. <hi>Benedict</hi> the 9. <hi>Silueſter</hi> the 3. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 6. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 18. <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> the 2. <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7. <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight,<note place="margin">Guicciard. lib. 1</note> and who not eyther by the diuell, deceite, fauour, force, or money attayned the Popedome. Here bawaes, cookes, horſkee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, children, and all for money, were preferred to Eccle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iaſticall dignities.<note place="margin">Aureum ſpccul. in Antilogia.</note> Here Paradiſe and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Iuſtice, &amp; iudgement, &amp; all for mony.<note place="margin">Theod. a Nien, lib. 1. cap. 68.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lib. 2. cap. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the 9. in a ſhort time got for pardons out of one kingdome an 100. thouſand <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens. O Roma, laetare ſuper iniquitates
<pb facs="tcp:14671:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>filiorum hominum:</hi> ô <hi>Rome</hi> reioyce ouer iniquitie,<note place="margin">Abbas Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpergeſ. Th. Beck. epiſt. ad Archi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. Mogunt.</note> for it is thy harueſt. Yea their holy Saint and ſeruant <hi>Becket</hi> could thus report of <hi>Rome, factam eſſem meretricem et proſtituta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe pro mercede,</hi> that ſhe made her ſelfe a common harlot for money. How long might I dwell vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſurfetting and drunkenneſſe.<note place="margin">Guicciard. lib. 1. &amp; lib. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centius</hi> the 8. <hi>totum ſe voluptatibus et otio tradidit,</hi> betooke himſelfe to pleaſure and idleneſſe. But <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the 6. was much more bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh: for <hi>nullum habuit religionis ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum:</hi> he had no ſence of religion.<note place="margin">Onuphrius. Sanazarius.</note> Authour are all to bepeſtered with the gluttonie,<note place="margin">Guicciard lib. 7. &amp; lib. 14. Platina.</note> lecherie, Sodomie, and inceſt of <hi>Iulius</hi> the 2. <hi>Leo</hi> the 10. <hi>Paulus</hi> the 3. <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 4. <hi>Paulus</hi> the 2. <hi>Pius</hi> the 4. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 12. <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie</hi> the 7. <hi>Sergius</hi> the 3. &amp; other: in ſuch ſort as <hi>Luiprand</hi> calleth the <hi>Lateran</hi> pallace <hi>proſtibulum mere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Agrip. de Leno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cin, &amp; de va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. ſcient.</note> a common ſtewes: famous
<pb facs="tcp:14671:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>are the murders and diſcordes of <hi>Gregorie</hi> the 7. <hi>Iohn</hi> the 11. in poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning their predeceſſors,<note place="margin">Onuphrius Epi. Otho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. imperat. ad Iohan. papa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Luitprand. lib. 6. cap. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Formoſus, Romanus, Sergius</hi> and the reſt. Not to rip vp their crueltie euen vnto the dead: as to <hi>Wickleffe, Bucer, Paulus Phagius, Henry</hi> the fourth, the Admirall of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Benno Cardin. Cornel. Agrip. Platina.</note> Popes vnto Popes, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. The whole world is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their pride, in their triple crowne, <hi>Ganimedes,</hi> Muſicians,<note place="margin">Bernard. lib. 4. de conſid. &amp; in cant. ſerm. 33.</note> ſtately Pallaces, purple, golde, ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, ſcepters, coronations &amp; pompe, Rings, Bracelets, Chaines, Iewels, Smaragdes, Adamantes, Saphyres,<note place="margin">Lib. 1. ceremo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ponufic. ſect. 3. c. p. 3.</note> Chryſolites, Iaſpers, and Vnions, toes kiſſed, ſtirrops held by Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, yea and if they liſt, they muſt ride vpon the ſhoulders of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors: <hi>O tempus peſsimum in quo defecit ſanctus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vita Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 9.</note> 
               <hi>et diminuta ſunt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritates, à filijs hominum:</hi> ô time,<note place="margin">Guicciard. li. 11. Platina in Paul. 2.</note> the worſt of all times, wherein the
<pb facs="tcp:14671:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>good man is periſhed,<note place="margin">Paſeiſ. temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mar. 2. Adrian 3. Stephan. 5. Platina in vita Dyoniſii primi.</note> and truth is departed from the ſonnes of mens vnto which times <hi>nil vel ſuperbiae Luxuriae, pompae addi poteſt:</hi> neither pride, pompe, or riotouſneſſe, can more be added. (Begin ſaith one of the Fathers <hi>Tidentine) à ſanctu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ario Dei ſi vllus iam pudor,</hi> &amp;c. at the ſanctuarie of God, if there be any ſhame, honeſtie,<note place="margin">In Svnod. Trid. ſeſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> or vertue to be found: <hi>vt merito poſsit mundus ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunca latronum dicior:</hi> ſo that the world may be well called a den of theeues,<note place="margin">Palingen. lib. 6.</note> wherein men with braſen faces, &amp; impure mouthes ſay, <hi>non eſt Deus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Synod. Trid. feſſ. 1.</note> there is no God. Whoſe beaſtly maners are ſo ill, &amp; conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation ſo brutiſh, as they haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken God,<note place="margin">Apoc. 18.</note> &amp; betaken themſelues vnto the Epicuir; ô then come out of her my people <hi>viuere qui recte cupitis diſcedite Roma omnia cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> licet non licet eſſe bonum;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Silu. 1.</note> for bleſſed is the man that delights in the law of the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> &amp; walkes not in the counſell
<pb facs="tcp:14671:56" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the wicked, nor leads his life like he ſinners &amp; vngodly. Wherefore ſeeing that papiſtry is a religion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixed &amp; compounded of error &amp; hereſies: ſeeing it is an Apoſtate church, and the kingdom of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt: ſeeing it refuſeth Chriſt to be the head therof, &amp; accepteth the Pope in his place &amp; roome: ſeeing it is a monſter hauing ſomtimes 2. ſomtimes 3. ſomtimes 4. heads at once: ſeeing it denies the auncient &amp; true God, &amp; ſets vp new &amp; falſe god, in his ſtead: ſeeing it diueſteth Chirſt of all his offices, &amp; beſtowes them vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fancies, &amp; vſurping flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; ſeeing it remooues Chriſt the true foundation, and builds it ſelfe vpon <hi>Sodomits,</hi> Magitians, Atheiſts and the diuels ſeruants: ſeeing it is an vſing, a Newter, and a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriſing church; ſeeing it is corrupt and too too rotten in the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke of religion: ſeeing it makes religion an arte of ſubtill pollicie:
<pb facs="tcp:14671:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſeeing it makes Chriſt a deepe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuer, and impoſtor: ſeeing it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermines the ſimple; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes the ſoule: ſeeing it makes a ieſt and playe of her Papiſticall profeſſion and religion: ſeeing it denies the holy ſeriptures to be the word of God, and coines new ſcriptures to her popiſh fancie and deuiſe: ſeeing it teacheth villanie and all vngodlineſſe: ſeeing it is an enemie to the good and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous murderer of the Saints: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſets vp Iudaiſme, Ethniciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, and foule Idolatry: ſeeing it makes no account of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor of his worſhip, and holy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eruice: ſeeing both heads and members are vnſound, vnſanorie, and moſt impure, both in doctrine, manners, and in all good liuing, we conclude that Papiſme is a masked Atheiſme.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:59"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:60"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:61"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:62"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:63"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:64"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:65"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:66"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:67"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:68"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:69"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:70"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:71"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:72"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:73"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:74"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:75"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:14671:76" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
